[UNKNOWN] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_11] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_01] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[UNKNOWN] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_11] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_14] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[UNKNOWN] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_04] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_14] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_13] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_15] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_14] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[UNKNOWN] Subtitles created by Amara.org community
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_14] Honorable Assembly, I now call upon Ágnes Forsthofer, who will say a few words.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly, esteemed colleagues, esteemed fellow citizens!
[SPEAKER_13] I am deeply honored to address you today, in gratitude for your trust.
[SPEAKER_13] I know precisely and understand exactly what responsibility the trust placed in me entails.
[SPEAKER_13] I know precisely that with this trust, I have not received power, but a service.
[SPEAKER_13] From my faith as well, I know that from those to whom much has been entrusted, much will be demanded.
[SPEAKER_13] Today is not a day for me, but for the Hungarian nation, opening a historical opportunity.
[SPEAKER_13] Changes are coming that will mark the beginning of a new era in the history of Hungarian parliamentary democracy.
[SPEAKER_13] For the National Assembly must once again be the home of the Hungarian nation, the house of Hungary, not the parties.
[UNKNOWN] It must not be a center of power, but a sanctuary of the will of the nation.
[SPEAKER_13] This house will once again be the house of humility and modesty, of service and the desire to act, not the level of lordliness, grandstanding, or self-display.
[SPEAKER_13] Where we are not better or worse than one another, but rather balance each other.
[SPEAKER_13] In every statement, we must strive for the unity of the Hungarian nation.
[SPEAKER_13] Let there be room here for argumentation, persuasion, understanding, respectful dialogue based on facts, and even for apologies.
[SPEAKER_13] And let there be room for love.
[SPEAKER_13] The first Hungarian female parliamentarian, Margit Slachta, stands before me as an example with her courageous stance, social sensitivity, and Christian commitment.
[SPEAKER_13] I quote her words.
[SPEAKER_13] Without love, a community has no life, no growth, and no success.
[SPEAKER_13] We will love our homeland in this house, we will love the Hungarian people.
[SPEAKER_13] And we will show this by creating laws that serve the honor and rise of the Hungarian nation with responsibility and integrity.
[SPEAKER_13] We will work so that no one is stigmatized, a second-class citizen,
[SPEAKER_13] because of their political opinion, lifestyle, or mode of work at the national assembly.
[SPEAKER_13] Let our country and our parliament once again belong to everyone who lives here, who works here, or whom the heart draws back from the wider world.
[SPEAKER_13] Let the voice of everyone reach these walls who entrusted us with their mandate through representation.
[SPEAKER_13] Let the work of the National Assembly be transparent and open.
[SPEAKER_13] Let it be more open toward the free press.
[SPEAKER_13] Let it be more understandable to civil society, and especially to the youth.
[SPEAKER_13] Let those who are interested clearly see and hear how we work for them.
[SPEAKER_13] Let them see that the world is diverse, and so is meaningful debate, but it is based on mutual respect.
[SPEAKER_13] Therefore, I ask my fellow representatives to transcend political opinions and jointly restore the image of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_13] Because the restoration of public trust begins here, in the parliament.
[SPEAKER_13] Let the work of the National Assembly be worthy of the mandate we received from the Hungarian people.
[SPEAKER_13] We do not serve the citizens of Hungary adequately when we are loud, but when, by understanding each other better, we are able to build bridges even over the chasms.
[SPEAKER_13] A new mindset is also needed in the leadership of the National Assembly office.
[SPEAKER_13] The maintenance of order must not serve as an excuse for limiting political opinions and retreating into isolation.
[SPEAKER_13] Value creation will not be manifested in measures and appearances that waste public funds and display power,
[SPEAKER_13] but in the new opportunities created through responsible management and in committed legislative work.
[SPEAKER_13] If we work this way, then according to the plan of Saint Stephen, our path will once again lead back to Europe.
[SPEAKER_13] Let the first symbolic step on this path be my first decision as Speaker.
[SPEAKER_13] I order that today, after 12 years, the flag of the European Union be returned to the building of the Hungarian parliament.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you very much!
[SPEAKER_13] This flag is the symbol of the alliance to which Hungarian voters gave an overwhelming majority in favor 22 years ago.
[SPEAKER_13] Belonging to this alliance remains today an elemental interest of the Hungarian nation.
[SPEAKER_13] Follow this first symbolic step with many others, through which we will once again become respected members of European communities.
[UNKNOWN] Expressing my gratitude once again, I now face this honorable task.
[SPEAKER_13] And I ask for God's blessing on the work of the National Assembly formed today and on the renewed Hungarian democracy.
[SPEAKER_13] Thank you!
[SPEAKER_14] Honorable National Assembly! I thank the words of our chairperson!
[SPEAKER_14] Honorable National Assembly! I kindly ask you to stand as we pay respects before the national flag and the historical flag are withdrawn!
[SPEAKER_05] Flag bearers, right, left!
[SPEAKER_05] Five! Step! In! Tuj!
[SPEAKER_14] Honorable National Assembly! Now, the election of the vice-presidents of the National Assembly, the vice-presidents responsible for legislation,
[SPEAKER_14] and the clerk will take place by open voting.
[SPEAKER_14] Honorable National Assembly! Based on a joint proposal from the leaders of the parliamentary groups, in my proposals numbered four and five, I propose that
[SPEAKER_14] the National Assembly elect six vice-presidents, including one responsible for legislation, and fourteen clerks.
[SPEAKER_14] Clerk, my apologies!
[SPEAKER_14] In accordance with the joint proposal, I propose that the National Assembly elect as vice-presidents Dr. Haller, Dr. Nagy Anikó, and Kőszegi Krisztián,
[SPEAKER_14] Vitályos Eszter from Fidesz, Dr. Latorcai Csaba, and Dr. Dúró Dóra,
[SPEAKER_14] as responsible vice-president for legislation Dr. Rákli Árpád,
[SPEAKER_14] Berki Ákos, Dr. Simón Zsuzsanna,
[SPEAKER_14] Néher András, Rózsahegyi Áron, Sóti Anikó Zsuzsanna,
[SPEAKER_14] Újvári Szilvia from Tisz, as well as Dr. Csúszda Gábor,
[SPEAKER_14] Újvári Szilviát Tisza , valamint dr. Csúszda Gábort ,
[SPEAKER_14] F. Sándor Kovács, Sándor Kovács, Lajos Balázs Németh, Gábor Varga from Fidesz,
[SPEAKER_14] Dr. István Simicsko from KDNP, and Dávid Dózs from Our Homeland are to be elected.
[SPEAKER_14] The proposer cannot submit a modifying proposal,
[SPEAKER_14] and the National Assembly decides on the officeholders individually without debate.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask the esteemed National Assembly to elect Dr. Hallerné, Dr. Nagyanikó as Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask you to vote!
[SPEAKER_14] I shall announce the decision.
[SPEAKER_14] 193 in favor, 0 against, and 0 abstentions.
[SPEAKER_14] Dr. Hallerné, Dr. Nagyanikó has been elected Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask the esteemed National Assembly to elect Krisztián Kőszegi as Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask you to vote now!
[SPEAKER_14] I shall announce the decision.
[SPEAKER_14] Krisztián Kőszegi has been elected by the National Assembly with 195 in favor, 0 against, and 0 abstentions.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask the esteemed National Assembly to elect Eszter Vitályos as Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly from May 13.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask you to vote!
[SPEAKER_14] I shall announce the decision.
[SPEAKER_14] The National Assembly has 195 in favor, 0 against, and 0 abstentions.
[SPEAKER_14] Eszter Vitályos has been elected Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask the esteemed National Assembly to elect Eszter Vitályos as Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly from May 13.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask you to vote!
[SPEAKER_14] I put to the vote of the esteemed National Assembly 195 yes, 0 no, and 0 abstentions.
[SPEAKER_14] Eszter Vitályos has been elected Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly.
[UNKNOWN] I put to the vote of the esteemed National Assembly 195 yes, 0 no, and 0 abstentions.
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_14] How many members of the National Assembly will there be?
[UNKNOWN] How many members of the National Assembly will there be?
[SPEAKER_14] Dorá Duró has been elected Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask the esteemed National Assembly to elect Dr. Rákri Hár as Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly responsible for legislative affairs.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask for the call of the house.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask the esteemed National Assembly, we are now deciding on the person of the Secretary of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask the esteemed National Assembly to elect Ákos Berki as Secretary of the National Assembly. Now vote!
[SPEAKER_14] I declare the decision. The National Assembly 195 yes, zero no, and zero abstentions.
[SPEAKER_14] Ákos Berki, Deputy Speaker of the esteemed National Assembly responsible for legislative affairs.
[SPEAKER_14] I have now elected Ákos Berki as Secretary of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I ask the esteemed National Assembly to elect István Bodóci as Secretary of the National Assembly. I ask you to vote!
[UNKNOWN] I ask the esteemed National Assembly to elect István Bodóci as Secretary of the National Assembly. I ask you to vote!
[SPEAKER_14] breakfast
[UNKNOWN] breakfast
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_14] breakfast
[SPEAKER_14]
[UNKNOWN] A small question.
[SPEAKER_14] I request the vote.
[UNKNOWN] I request the vote.
[SPEAKER_14] I shall announce the decision.
[SPEAKER_14] 195 in favor, 0 against, and 0 abstentions.
[SPEAKER_14] [SPEAKER_14] Rózsa Hegyi Áron has been elected as the secretary of the National Assembly.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_14] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_14]
[SPEAKER_14] [SPEAKER_14] I ask the esteemed National Assembly whether it wishes to elect Szilvia Újvári as the secretary of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I request the vote.
[SPEAKER_14] I shall announce the decision.
[SPEAKER_14] [SPEAKER_14] 195 in favor, 0 abstentions, and 0 against.
[SPEAKER_14] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_14]
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_14] Thank you.
[UNKNOWN]
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_14] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_14] The National Assembly 195. Yes, zero, not even zero abstentions, elected Dr. Gábor Csúza as the secretary of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I propose to the esteemed National Assembly that F. Sándor Kovács be elected as the secretary of the National Assembly. I ask for a vote now.
[SPEAKER_14] I declare the decision. 195. Yes, zero, not even zero abstentions, the National Assembly elected F. Sándor Kovács as the secretary of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_14] I propose to the esteemed National Assembly that Sándor Kovács be elected as the secretary of the National Assembly. I ask for a vote now.
[SPEAKER_14] I propose to the esteemed National Assembly that Balázs Laö Németh be elected as the secretary of the National Assembly. I ask for a vote now.
[SPEAKER_14] I propose to the esteemed National Assembly that Gábor Varga be elected as the secretary of the National Assembly. I ask for a vote now.
[SPEAKER_14] I propose to the esteemed National Assembly that Dr. István Simiskó be elected as the secretary of the National Assembly. I ask for a vote now.
[SPEAKER_14] Vice Presidents Kőszegi Krisztián, Vitályos Eszter, Dr. Latorcai Csaba, Dóra Dúró, Vice President Dr. Ráklihár responsible for legislative affairs, as well as Bújdosó Andrea, Anna Tisza, Fidesz Gergely Gulyás, KDNP Bence Rétvári, and László Torockai, leader of the Mi Hazánk faction.
[SPEAKER_14] Honorable National Assembly, the inaugural meeting of the committee of the whole will now take place.
[SPEAKER_14] In view of this, I now declare a 45-minute recess.
[SPEAKER_14] The members of the committee of the whole are kindly requested to proceed to the Pázmándi Dénes Room, number 11, on the main floor.
[SPEAKER_14] After the recess, I will hand over the chairmanship to Ágnes Forshoffer, the house officer, as she says, and I would also like to thank the notaries for their work.
[SPEAKER_14] Thank you for your cooperation.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you for watching.
[SPEAKER_11] Thank you for watching.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you for watching.
[SPEAKER_01] And they set up the place there, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, they set it up.
[SPEAKER_01] And therefore, the furniture for the office was made according to the plans of Stenéli Imre and one of his young assistants,
[SPEAKER_01] according to the plans of Főrk Ernő, this office furniture was made,
[SPEAKER_01] about which it should be noted that these are made of mahogany, or mahogany veneer,
[SPEAKER_01] that is, furniture made with mahogany veneer applied on a beechwood core,
[SPEAKER_01] practically a writing desk, a small living room suite, chairs, a coffee table,
[SPEAKER_01] down to the writing set, so the architects planned everything.
[SPEAKER_01] And besides the mahogany, which perhaps even more enhances the representativeness of the piece,
[SPEAKER_01] there are Zsolnai inlays, and on these Zsolnai inlays there are motifs taken from Hungarian folk art.
[SPEAKER_01] It is a very decorative table, I won't say it would suit everyone's taste,
[SPEAKER_01] but it is indeed a very decorative and beautiful suite, and an important memory of Hungarian furniture art up until the end of the 19th century.
[SPEAKER_01] By the way, parts of it also include various seating arrangements,
[SPEAKER_01] and it is very interesting to observe that Főrk Ernő, who designed this, was a young architect at the time.
[SPEAKER_01] and Tendülel, who was already older, and significantly more receptive, so to speak, to contemporary trends.
[SPEAKER_01] And that at the turn of the century, this historizing furniture art began to be
[SPEAKER_01] left behind by everyone.
[SPEAKER_01] This meant that at the time, they thought of furniture a bit like small buildings,
[SPEAKER_01] and attached all sorts of architectural details to them.
[SPEAKER_01] For example, we can now see the chair of the presiding officer in the middle,
[SPEAKER_01] so, by the way, Gothic and Neo-Gothic motifs are present on its back.
[SPEAKER_01] So these pieces of furniture were not necessarily about comfort at that time,
[SPEAKER_01] but rather much more about the fact that certain architects began designing them,
[SPEAKER_01] and they were rather representative pieces.
[SPEAKER_01] However, in this prime ministerial furniture suite, for example, the chairs
[SPEAKER_01] already clearly showed solutions that combined contemporary English furniture design with Hungarian traditions,
[SPEAKER_01] and they are actually very beautiful pieces.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, this room did not survive the 20th century entirely unscathed,
[SPEAKER_01] so, by the way, a few pieces of it have gone missing,
[SPEAKER_01] but these were reconstructed over the past twenty years.
[SPEAKER_11] Yes, a few things went missing around here, we noticed that.
[SPEAKER_01] So Paris was thus awarded, it received an award there, in fact, practically everyone was awarded in Paris,
[SPEAKER_01] so this does not really mean such a big thing,
[SPEAKER_01] and then, of course, they brought it back, and nicely incorporated it into this first-floor south-facing room.
[SPEAKER_01] This was often not sufficient for the then prime minister,
[SPEAKER_01] so the prime minister's office was not always and continuously located here,
[SPEAKER_01] but it was here in the most recent period.
[SPEAKER_11] You mentioned some things that are very exciting about the house's internal little secrets behind the scenes,
[SPEAKER_11] or if there are such interesting or curious details about the building,
[SPEAKER_11] for example, what special features the presidential chair has.
[SPEAKER_11] If you could tell us a few of these, I think we would be happy to savor and listen to them.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, since we are at the presidential chair, of course we can imagine,
[SPEAKER_01] during longer sessions, of course, they switch chairpersons, they change,
[SPEAKER_01] so one of the vice chairpersons comes in, or two vice chairpersons alternate,
[SPEAKER_01] and we all know that when we sit in a chair for a long time,
[SPEAKER_01] we transfer our body heat to that chair.
[SPEAKER_01] So that the next vice chairperson, or the chairperson who would sit in this warm chair,
[SPEAKER_01] can simply, with a single arm movement, by pulling a metal lever,
[SPEAKER_01] practically flip the seating surface,
[SPEAKER_01] which is symmetrically designed on both sides,
[SPEAKER_01] so the next person to take over the session can sit on a fresh, so to speak, cool cushion.
[SPEAKER_11] And by the way, what is the practice regarding this, do you know whether it is used or applied today,
[SPEAKER_11] or do they just leave it as is, assuming that no one needs to flip it, and it is not necessary to ask for it.
[SPEAKER_11] What is the practical approach?
[SPEAKER_01] You see, I don't know, I would say it's worth watching the parliamentary broadcasts,
[SPEAKER_01] to catch this, but what I do know is that the system itself,
[SPEAKER_01] I've also seen it up close, is actually quite simple to operate,
[SPEAKER_01] so there is no fundamental obstacle to it.
[SPEAKER_11] The fact that this works easily will certainly be practical for the future, in my opinion.
[SPEAKER_11] What else is worth knowing about the building, perhaps?
[SPEAKER_11] Is there anything, for example about the dome, right, it's also a very special thing there,
[SPEAKER_11] if you could tell us a few things about it?
[SPEAKER_11] How high it is, etc.
[SPEAKER_11] You know, 96...
[SPEAKER_01] The top of the dome is at 96 meters high,
[SPEAKER_01] some may remember that during the decades of socialism
[SPEAKER_01] the red star was there.
[SPEAKER_01] On top, but originally and in its original form, it looked like this.
[SPEAKER_01] On top, by the way, there is also such a small upper circular railing,
[SPEAKER_01] the architectural term for this is basically "laterna," meaning a lantern.
[SPEAKER_01] This is the finishing element of the Gothic tower peaks.
[SPEAKER_01] By the way, one can go out there, obviously primarily those
[SPEAKER_01] who carry out the maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01] What might be interesting is that, and few people know,
[SPEAKER_01] if we were to walk into the building, and the visitors,
[SPEAKER_01] I mean the people,
[SPEAKER_01] see the Holy Crown and the dome hall,
[SPEAKER_01] then we are in the dome hall.
[SPEAKER_01] But the dome hall is actually not exactly where we would expect it to be
[SPEAKER_01] based on the building's exterior.
[SPEAKER_01] This dome is significantly taller.
[SPEAKER_01] There is an outer and an inner dome,
[SPEAKER_01] and between the two there is almost as much attic space again.
[SPEAKER_01] This is the attic space of the dome.
[SPEAKER_01] This was necessary because the internal architectural concept
[SPEAKER_01] and the external urban visual appearance required different proportions,
[SPEAKER_01] and therefore the two separate from each other.
[SPEAKER_01] But what is interesting, for example, is that the largest chandelier in the parliament,
[SPEAKER_01] I won't say how many bulbs are in it now, but it is over a hundred,
[SPEAKER_01] can have its bulbs replaced in such a way
[SPEAKER_01] that someone from the upper dome hall can climb down a ladder
[SPEAKER_01] into the chandelier.
[SPEAKER_01] It practically has a small interior space,
[SPEAKER_01] it can accommodate a person, and then they can reach out nicely,
[SPEAKER_01] one can be very careful, there is actually a net,
[SPEAKER_01] so that is why it does not drop the light bulb,
[SPEAKER_01] the person does not accidentally touch the Holy Crown display case here,
[SPEAKER_01] but from there, one can practically replace the burnt-out light bulbs, for example.
[SPEAKER_01] This is an interesting procedure.
[SPEAKER_11] I don't know if this story is true,
[SPEAKER_11] but I heard that it was a long time ago, or not,
[SPEAKER_11] and you will correct me shortly,
[SPEAKER_11] and from now on, I will also know it correctly,
[SPEAKER_11] that there was a time when you had to replace all of them at once,
[SPEAKER_11] or perhaps only one, or was there none like that?
[SPEAKER_01] I don't know anything about this.
[SPEAKER_11] Then you must know it well,
[SPEAKER_11] so I have no doubt about that,
[SPEAKER_11] that I must have heard or heard it differently.
[SPEAKER_11] Fundamentally, how did history pass through the house?
[SPEAKER_11] So, there were wars here, revolutions,
[SPEAKER_11] how did the building experience this,
[SPEAKER_11] what kind of damage does it have, as far as I know,
[SPEAKER_11] that there are still specific places today,
[SPEAKER_11] where, as you know, there are still bullet marks,
[SPEAKER_11] which have been preserved during the reconstructions.
[SPEAKER_11] So, what is the relationship between this stormy year in history and the building,
[SPEAKER_11] if we were to talk about it?
[SPEAKER_01] As you know, it is very interesting that almost immediately,
[SPEAKER_01] just a few years after the building is handed over,
[SPEAKER_01] I should know the exact date,
[SPEAKER_01] around 1904 there is quite a big disturbance in the chamber,
[SPEAKER_01] when the opposition members of parliament,
[SPEAKER_01] who were then the opposition members,
[SPEAKER_01] pile up the furniture of the chamber into large heaps,
[SPEAKER_01] supposedly smashing it to pieces.
[SPEAKER_01] There are also contemporary photographs in the Sunday newspaper,
[SPEAKER_01] which report on this event in a shocked manner.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I haven't noted that yet.
[SPEAKER_01] In truth, this was not such a great damage.
[SPEAKER_01] As you know, during the Second World War, the building
[SPEAKER_01] suffers quite serious damage.
[SPEAKER_01] These, however, are dwarfed by the fact,
[SPEAKER_01] for example, that the royal palace suffered back then.
[SPEAKER_01] but the House of Lords, for example,
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, when we confront it,
[SPEAKER_01] is located on the right side.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, the parliament does not sit there now,
[SPEAKER_01] but in the House of Representatives,
[SPEAKER_01] and if we confront the building on the left side,
[SPEAKER_01] that is, the part closer to the metro.
[SPEAKER_01] So the House of Lords, for example, received quite a few hits,
[SPEAKER_01] including a direct hit in the chamber itself,
[SPEAKER_01] the ceiling was damaged, the furnishings were damaged, almost destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01] So the house does not survive World War II unscathed,
[SPEAKER_01] and especially you mentioned these shell marks,
[SPEAKER_01] which were left in certain places on the façade,
[SPEAKER_01] they, I mean, marked the entire house everywhere back then.
[SPEAKER_01] So in 1945, in addition to that,
[SPEAKER_01] by then the building's exterior had already become quite run-down,
[SPEAKER_01] many factories were still operating in the area,
[SPEAKER_01] the air was actually very polluted compared to today's air quality,
[SPEAKER_01] and the building's façade began to blacken quite a lot,
[SPEAKER_01] but these scars look fresh on it.
[SPEAKER_01] on nearly post-World War II photographs.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, in any case, these damages were basically
[SPEAKER_01] repaired in a few years, roughly a decade.
[SPEAKER_01] Some are not restored exactly as they were, but there are few such cases,
[SPEAKER_01] and actually, from that point onward, what was noticeable in recent times,
[SPEAKER_01] is not so much the storm of history,
[SPEAKER_01] as the quality of the original stone material used,
[SPEAKER_01] because the building was continuously behind scaffolding.
[SPEAKER_01] We remember this, it was like that until 2014.
[SPEAKER_01] This was necessary because such a large quantity of stone was needed for the façades,
[SPEAKER_01] that the best quality class of stone could not be supplied quickly enough by Hungarian quarries,
[SPEAKER_01] and therefore, sometimes lower quality shipments were also accepted,
[SPEAKER_01] and these stones, in fact, did not withstand the test of time as well.
[SPEAKER_01] There are already known photographs from 1907, so barely after the building was handed over,
[SPEAKER_01] showing that certain small Gothic details, such as small towers, were already missing in some places.
[SPEAKER_01] So, in fact, the restoration of the façade began in the 1920s,
[SPEAKER_01] and the house was practically always behind scaffolding, going around the building,
[SPEAKER_01] and there was the idea that they would go all the way around, slowly becoming visible from the front,
[SPEAKER_01] but that is not the case, because in fact, a significant part of the stones were replaced during the 20th century,
[SPEAKER_01] they were simply re-carved following the originals, but there are still original stones in the walls of the house.
[SPEAKER_01] And in the end, of course, the most noticeable thing, this already mentioned red star,
[SPEAKER_01] was installed on a great many public buildings almost immediately in the 1950s.
[SPEAKER_01] It was a rather large star, and it could also be illuminated from the inside at night.
[SPEAKER_01] This, by the way, caused some problems, because when it first encountered a heavy rain,
[SPEAKER_01] the reflectors inside these red glass panels heated them up so much,
[SPEAKER_01] that they cracked from the cold rain.
[SPEAKER_01] And eventually, they built various kinds of grilles around it to offer some protection from the rain.
[SPEAKER_01] In 1956, by the way, they tried to cut this star down.
[SPEAKER_01] Allegedly, there was an industrial welder,
[SPEAKER_01] who climbed up at great risk to his life to cut it down from there,
[SPEAKER_01] but in the end, he did not succeed.
[SPEAKER_01] It is a rather massive structure, and from an architectural and heritage perspective, I say at least,
[SPEAKER_01] that it is not a bad thing that he did not succeed, because it is a structure weighing several hundred kilograms.
[SPEAKER_01] If a person were to cut it down from there, it would fall down,
[SPEAKER_01] and God knows where it would land, or where it would come to rest.
[SPEAKER_01] However, this star was fortunate in that in 1990, or 1989,
[SPEAKER_01] part of the dome had just been scaffolded.
[SPEAKER_01] And because of this, the star could be relatively easily reached to be removed.
[SPEAKER_01] There were various offers, supposedly, and some wanted to take it away by helicopter,
[SPEAKER_01] as a spectacular, theatrical gesture.
[SPEAKER_01] It would have been a removal, yes.
[SPEAKER_01] In the end, it was disassembled into pieces, placed into boxes, this star,
[SPEAKER_01] and was handed over to the collection of the National Museum.
[SPEAKER_01] However, since 2015, at the exhibition in the visitor center,
[SPEAKER_01] it is already presented as a museum object, representing one of the periods of history,
[SPEAKER_01] and can be viewed.
[SPEAKER_01] This star, by the way, is here in the house, this star is here.
[SPEAKER_11] In a few words, let us talk about the fact that there were also famous, legendary assassinations in the house.
[SPEAKER_11] So, in fact, a gun was fired specifically there,
[SPEAKER_11] where just now Ágnes Forsthofer took her oath.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, there was an assassination attempt against Tisza.
[SPEAKER_01] The date of this is again a bit...
[SPEAKER_01] I think I would guess around the 20th.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, and supposedly the prime minister,
[SPEAKER_01] to the extent that I would say, was a man of strong nerves,
[SPEAKER_01] so supposedly he even made a comment that he could still practice,
[SPEAKER_01] because not only are his speeches bad, but he can't even shoot.
[SPEAKER_11] Yes, because, as you know, three shots were fired at him, and all three missed,
[SPEAKER_11] and the bullet marks or shooting marks are still visible in the tree today.
[SPEAKER_01] By the way, the bullet mark is still there today in the presidential rostrum,
[SPEAKER_01] they kind of left it as a memento back then,
[SPEAKER_01] and afterward, no one bothered it.
[SPEAKER_01] So yes, there were moments like that.
[SPEAKER_11] But according to the legend, the assassin, after failing to hit,
[SPEAKER_11] shot himself in the head, and that also failed.
[SPEAKER_11] So he survived that as well.
[SPEAKER_11] So, that it was such a...
[SPEAKER_11] A botched assassination attempt.
[SPEAKER_11] Yes, so it was such an assassination attempt,
[SPEAKER_11] and I think there was another one earlier,
[SPEAKER_11] as I read somewhere, when they shot at the Speaker from the gallery,
[SPEAKER_11] none of the shots hit their target there either,
[SPEAKER_11] so basically, it didn’t result in any injuries,
[SPEAKER_11] and I don’t know, if I have to think suddenly,
[SPEAKER_11] then another assassination attempt comes to mind from modern political history,
[SPEAKER_11] the one committed by Gyula Horn against József Tőkés,
[SPEAKER_11] when he called him Pubi.
[SPEAKER_11] But otherwise, other assassination attempts don’t come to mind now.
[SPEAKER_01] There was also a small rocket attack in the 1990s
[SPEAKER_01] incidentally, right here on the stairs.
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] Indeed, otherwise, one could get quite close to the parliament building back then,
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] and then, of course, this security zone was established,
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] which, at that time, was significantly larger than the current security zone.
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] And indeed, nowadays, in normal operation, so to speak,
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] meaning when there is no event on Kossuth Square,
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] then although one cannot go up onto the steps,
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] one can still get quite close to them—for example, to the lions.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] We have already spoken a lot about the building, the parliamentary building,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] but the fact of how this building is, determines to a large extent,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] how we live, move, exist, and even now, how so many of us are gathered here on this square,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] refers to Kossuth Square itself.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] If you were to tell us about it, why the square is like this, what iconic sites it has,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] why these sites are like this, and how the form we know came about?
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] This could potentially be a rather long monologue, so I will try to be brief.
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] Indeed, the building itself, as we mentioned in our earlier conversation,
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] created an entirely new situation, and around it, they formed a new square.
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] Indeed, there were not very significant buildings here, so they could demolish some of them.
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] Incidentally, the square itself was occupied by two things.
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] The southern part, where we are sitting, was roughly this area that was empty,
[SPEAKER_01] [SPEAKER_01] which was the aforementioned filling ground.
[SPEAKER_01] On the northern part, there was a so-called shipping office,
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, here, related to the Danube shipping, such an administrative institution.
[SPEAKER_01] They handled matters, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_01] They broke down the cases, and actually regulated them only slightly,
[SPEAKER_01] just the street network that had developed around the area by then.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean Nádor Street, which opens into the southern side of Kossuth Square,
[SPEAKER_01] and Falkmiksa Street, which, I mean, is its continuation beyond,
[SPEAKER_01] formed a single street previously.
[SPEAKER_01] They made a slight change to the angle of this, so that the square would be larger and more uniform,
[SPEAKER_01] but actually, they adjusted the regulation a little on the northern and southern sides,
[SPEAKER_01] but there was no need for further regulation.
[SPEAKER_01] As a result, the square is a bit irregular, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01] This is not noticeable, because the architect and the architecture in the area do everything to prevent it from being noticed,
[SPEAKER_01] but in reality, from north to south, the square becomes wider and wider.
[SPEAKER_01] If we look at the northern side and check how wide the building there is,
[SPEAKER_01] and then look at the side of the metro entrance, we can see this difference.
[SPEAKER_01] This is why, when the idea arose in 1905, 1906, or even earlier,
[SPEAKER_01] to place the equestrian statue of Gyula Andrássy here,
[SPEAKER_01] the question arose: fine, but where should we put it?
[SPEAKER_01] And when they installed it, they did it back then by practically creating small scale models, like little paper cutouts,
[SPEAKER_01] by practically cutting out a one-to-one model of the statue from paper,
[SPEAKER_01] and they moved this around on rollers on the square.
[SPEAKER_01] And when they placed it in the center of Kossuth Square, it was not called that back then,
[SPEAKER_01] it was called Országház Square back then, and they realized then that this was not good,
[SPEAKER_01] because it emphasized this small irregularity even more.
[SPEAKER_01] And for this reason, Andrássy's statue was placed in front of the southern façade of the Országház.
[SPEAKER_01] And then the next statue erected is the Kossuth statue.
[SPEAKER_01] They erected his statue in 1927, and at that time the square was also renamed Kossuth Lajos Square,
[SPEAKER_01] and again the same problem arose: if we wanted to, we would place the statue in the center of the square,
[SPEAKER_01] and again they realized that no, this statue should not be placed in the center,
[SPEAKER_01] and that is why it was placed where it is, slightly towards the western end of the square.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, of course, comes the statue of Rákóczi, which is placed opposite to it, and then, of course, the statue of István Tisza on the western part of the square,
[SPEAKER_01] so this four-statue layout more or less emerged, and in fact, even the namesake of the square,
[SPEAKER_01] Kossuth's statue is not in a central or central position, but rather scattered like this.
[SPEAKER_11] It is really exciting and very interesting, for example, that you mentioned the aszló staff,
[SPEAKER_11] which was raised in the center of the square, but to what extent is this the center of the square, or how central is it actually,
[SPEAKER_11] and I suppose it should be exactly halfway along the building, or I would assume that,
[SPEAKER_11] but you will soon tell us what the reality is.
[SPEAKER_01] The problem here is that if we really want to go into this in detail,
[SPEAKER_01] theoretically, one should arrive at the square from Alkotmány Street,
[SPEAKER_01] then we see the main entrance of the parliament building, with the dome above it,
[SPEAKER_01] as the parliament is fundamentally aligned with the Danube, and because of the Danube, it is slightly angled,
[SPEAKER_01] and therefore the dome is actually a bit to the south of this axis.
[SPEAKER_01] And this is the problem, because if we place any object into this position,
[SPEAKER_01] it slightly draws attention to this, and as far as I know, these axes are very neatly composed,
[SPEAKER_01] so whether arriving from the direction of Alkotmány Street or exiting through the main entrance of the parliament,
[SPEAKER_01] these are two axes intersecting at an angle, and the flagpole was placed exactly at their intersection point.
[SPEAKER_01] So it ended up precisely in the epicenter of this irregularity,
[SPEAKER_01] but it is a flagpole, not a statue, not a large, extended composition, and the square could handle it.
[SPEAKER_11] Since when has tram traffic been operating on this square, so this wasn't the case from the very beginning?
[SPEAKER_01] No, although quite early, in 1908, if I remember correctly, the then transportation company put it into operation,
[SPEAKER_01] from here at Kossuth Square, because on the southern side there were already trams earlier,
[SPEAKER_01] they just didn't go this far, and then they extended it all the way to the Margit Bridge head, and even further,
[SPEAKER_01] and by the way, in the heroic age of tram transportation, it wasn't just a single line that ran here,
[SPEAKER_01] now, by the way, it's not just a single one either, because the number two tram, tram number 23,
[SPEAKER_01] several trams run this route, but there were actually many trams, 4-5 different lines that connected the city to various points,
[SPEAKER_01] so not only the Danube-side line, but also all the way to Városliget Park, and in other directions as well from here.
[SPEAKER_11] Also, don't forget, I recently read that there was a competition for the world's most beautiful tram routes,
[SPEAKER_11] or something similar, and I believe the route of tram number two actually won in that,
[SPEAKER_11] so there was a year when it was chosen as the world's most beautiful tram route at some event, if there was one.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, and in this regard, yes, it's quite thorough,
[SPEAKER_01] as you can beautifully admire the Danube panorama all the way through the Pest inner city.
[SPEAKER_01] A particularity regarding the square is that this is the only place on the Budapest tram network,
[SPEAKER_01] where the speed limit is not due to the condition of the track, but because this is a pedestrian zone even on weekdays.
[SPEAKER_11] Yes, many cyclists come as well.
[SPEAKER_01] A cycling zone, and that is why the tram does not run at the maximum speed of 50 km per hour,
[SPEAKER_01] which the condition of the track would otherwise allow, but rather slowed down to 25 km per hour,
[SPEAKER_01] and in this way, it is generally not dangerous for pedestrians.
[SPEAKER_11] If someone were to step out accidentally, there is time.
[SPEAKER_01] It regularly happens that someone gets so absorbed, for example, in photographing a building, that they don't notice the tram approaching.
[SPEAKER_11] So basically, the whole system is designed for that—people to get absorbed, and if someone does, the tram can at most sound its horn angrily once.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, if I may, I would like to return to the history of the square, because apart from the statues, it is very important what buildings stand on the square,
[SPEAKER_01] and obviously the parliament building is a starting point.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] Opposite the parliament, if we turn our back to it, we can see two buildings, or rather just one now, as the ministry is under scaffolding,
[SPEAKER_01] one of which is the office building, or rather the headquarters, of the Ministry of Agriculture, which was previously the Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Development.
[SPEAKER_01] This building began to be constructed at the same time as the parliament, in 1885, and was specifically placed here because it is visible that a government center is being formed,
[SPEAKER_01] and it was completed by 1887, so in two years, meaning the parliament continued to see the building as a construction site for quite some time,
[SPEAKER_01] and next to it, to the north, which most people know from the past decades as the Ethnographic Museum,
[SPEAKER_01] this is the Palace of Justice, which housed the highest judicial institution of the Royal Hungarian Court.
[SPEAKER_11] By the way, excuse me, there were a lot of exhibitions going on here in the vicinity, so from the WordPress photo, quite a lot of things that could be shown.
[SPEAKER_01] And a lot of films were also shot here.
[SPEAKER_11] Films were made, yes, yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, this is a very special thing, because there are not many governments or state centers in the world
[SPEAKER_01] where the buildings of the three branches of power—the legislature, the parliament, the judiciary,
[SPEAKER_01] the Palace of Justice, and the executive, the building of the Ministry of the Interior—stand together in such a beautiful triad.
[SPEAKER_01] As far as I know, actually, there is a similar arrangement in Washington,
[SPEAKER_01] but nowhere else in any other European or capital city.
[SPEAKER_01] That such a strong architectural and urban design gesture simultaneously shows the most beautiful,
[SPEAKER_01] or most important setting of civil power. So, in a way, Kossuth Square is formed by these three points.
[SPEAKER_11] Another interesting thing came to my mind, you mentioned how the parliament contains so many interesting things,
[SPEAKER_11] and how many, I don’t know, secret tunnels are inside it, for example.
[SPEAKER_11] Cellars, places where one could hear from here, whether the deputies could be evacuated in case of any trouble,
[SPEAKER_11] there are secret tunnels, anything else like that—can you tell us about it,
[SPEAKER_11] since if we are on site, the technology obviously doesn’t capture these things immediately, because it would give it away.
[SPEAKER_01] The parliamentary guard would take them away, but obviously it would be difficult to talk about secret tunnels,
[SPEAKER_01] now, I don’t actually know about any secret tunnels.
[SPEAKER_01] I had a fairly thorough opportunity to explore the cellars of the building,
[SPEAKER_01] and there are, in fact, connections to the house.
[SPEAKER_01] From the very beginning, one of the house’s special features was that it had district heating.
[SPEAKER_01] but the district heating didn't come from too far away.
[SPEAKER_01] The boiler house was located in the courtyard of one of the tenement houses on Balassi-Bálint Street, that is, on the street leading towards Jászai-Mariáter.
[SPEAKER_01] and essentially, a tunnel from the boiler house brought the heat to the parliament building.
[SPEAKER_01] There was a need for this because during the planning, they told Steinlein that building such a neo-Gothic structure
[SPEAKER_01] right next to a river, and then putting in heating and a chimney, would make it look very much like a steamboat,
[SPEAKER_01] and he wanted to avoid this, to prevent it from looking like something like that, so they moved it out of the building,
[SPEAKER_01] and this, by the way, is still in operation for the parliament building, it has long since been a modernized boiler house,
[SPEAKER_01] so there was, in fact, a utility tunnel from there to the building.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, apart from this, the building has always, of course, been sinking upwards, and there is certainly a connection with the metro, because the deputies...
[SPEAKER_11] But, how should I put it, in Hungarian colloquial speech and for all of us who are here and follow the broadcast,
[SPEAKER_11] I think everyone has heard under every government that which leader wanted to have a private metro stop for themselves here,
[SPEAKER_11] so obviously this was a kind of poem and a kind of bomo, with which people have just been joking around for decades, I don't know,
[SPEAKER_11] but these were, are, just rumors.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, regarding the rumors, the metro construction, the second metro, today's red line, construction began at the beginning of the 1950s, during the bloodiest period of the Cold War, everyone was afraid of a nuclear war,
[SPEAKER_01] and indeed, bomb shelters that were nuclear-proof were being built.
[SPEAKER_01] The metro itself, by the way, is a nuclear-proof bomb shelter, and to this day it is, in fact, a civil defense facility,
[SPEAKER_01] and the metro has, or had, the property that it was, so to speak, rerouted here to Kossuth Square afterwards,
[SPEAKER_01] because according to the original plans, the east-west metro line would not have come this way,
[SPEAKER_01] but rather, following the centuries-old transportation route, crossing under the Elizabeth Bridge, through Krisztinaváros, it would have reached the North-Buda area behind the Castle Hill,
[SPEAKER_01] hanem az évszázadok óta meglévő közlekedési vonalat követve, hogy az Erzsébet híd alatt átmenve, ugye Krisztinavároson keresztül érte volna el a Várhegy mögött az Észak-Budai részt,
[SPEAKER_01] but because the parliament building is located here,
[SPEAKER_01] the plans were modified accordingly, and the metro was redirected in this direction, back when it was still on the drawing board.
[SPEAKER_01] Indeed, shelters were built in connection with the metro, which were told to the workers that they were building the metro,
[SPEAKER_01] but in reality, a separate nuclear-proof shelter was built, but this is located under, or connected to, the party headquarters on Akadémia Street, and not the parliament.
[SPEAKER_01] And, of course, the parliament does not have such a connection,
[SPEAKER_01] because if we think about it, during the fifties, in the communist era, the parliament essentially had the role of a kind of cosmetic patch, and I was being quite polite in my phrasing.
[SPEAKER_01] I could tell stories about that.
[SPEAKER_01] So, in fact, the substantive decisions were not made in this building, and the most important people were not necessarily in this building.
[SPEAKER_01] The parliament, by the way, does have its own shelter under the building, which was initially created during World War II, and these were modernized in the fifties,
[SPEAKER_01] but these were not nuclear-proof shelters.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't know about a connection to the metro, but there is a connection that was built recently, the building above the metro, which was renovated quite significantly recently,
[SPEAKER_01] so it was demolished, and a new building was constructed over the metro exit, and this building, the Szabadgyörgy office building, has an underground tunnel, which connects it, and this is not a secret, it is publicly known, connecting it to the parliament building.
[SPEAKER_01] The practical reason for this, of course, is that the staff of the parliamentary office work in that building, and I understand that the Tisza faction is also going to move in there,
[SPEAKER_01] and the practical reason is simply that when someone enters the secure zone, they can pass through to the building without having to exit and re-enter.
[SPEAKER_01] So the building has two connections.
[SPEAKER_01] With other parts, and I should also add that outside the building, the visitor center and the underground garage of the parliament are located on the building's night side.
[SPEAKER_01] Naturally, these are connected to the building, and there are three points where you can pass through. Tourists have one or two passageways, and the parliamentary staff have another.
[SPEAKER_11] I really feel a bit like it's good that we came here today, beyond the amazing things happening in the parliament building,
[SPEAKER_11] but also because of this free exhibition tour and the historical background provided, which we are truly grateful for.
[SPEAKER_11] Just one last question, if I may, and then I won't keep you, about the fact that you mentioned heating was outsourced, but the cooling of this large building is also a separate story and a separate tale,
[SPEAKER_11] which you will then tell us whether it's true or not, but that theoretically there were places where huge ice blocks were brought in and the ventilation system was directed onto them,
[SPEAKER_11] how this works, how they came up with this idea, how practical it was, and, by the way, how well the cooling actually works inside, since there are no air conditioners on the walls, as we can see.
[SPEAKER_01] We now find ourselves in a delicate situation where an art historian has to speak interestingly about building engineering issues, but I'll try.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, this icy story is known by many, originally it didn't work like that, because we mentioned that the statues,
[SPEAKER_01] and both the heating and cooling of the building came from external locations. We already discussed the heating, and the cooling was arranged in such a way that
[SPEAKER_01] they built two tunnels, each about 45 to 50 meters long, beneath the square. We know that if you put something underground, like a cellar, we go down into the cellar, and it's cold there.
[SPEAKER_01] They actually made use of the fact that in these tunnels, they let in the outside air from above through fountains.
[SPEAKER_01] The fountain was good not only for cooling the air but also for filtering it from dust and soot.
[SPEAKER_01] In these tunnels, they sucked in this air, and they were actually able to produce a cool, low-temperature air of about ten degrees,
[SPEAKER_01] and with the help of various fans and suitable spaces, they could bring this cold air under the assembly rooms.
[SPEAKER_01] However, the system didn't work entirely like that, because the precise temperature, the relatively precise temperature, didn't function like a modern thermostat,
[SPEAKER_01] where you can set it to a tenth of a degree, for example, to specify the desired temperature.
[SPEAKER_01] By appropriately mixing the warm air coming from the boiler room,
[SPEAKER_01] they could practically set a fairly specific temperature, and this air reached the assembly rooms,
[SPEAKER_01] and simply by the gravity of the cold and warm air, it reached the deputies below.
[SPEAKER_01] By the way, under each chair there is a small grid, and through that, this pre-set cold, cool, or even warm air would rise.
[SPEAKER_01] And the extraction of this air was handled from above, the chandeliers were suitable for this, these are open structures,
[SPEAKER_01] through which they sucked in the air from the space, and thus created a kind of air current in which it was pleasant to work.
[SPEAKER_11] Despite the need to address and resolve these issues.
[SPEAKER_11] Another interesting situation arose regarding the size of the chairs, we spoke about this, how precisely defined these dimensions were.
[SPEAKER_11] And this is another legend, perhaps the representative is no longer alive, perhaps they called him András Rabcsák,
[SPEAKER_11] for whom, theoretically, a chair had to be modified.
[SPEAKER_11] So, whether the chairs, or you will adjust them, whether it was like that or not.
[SPEAKER_11] And how far back into history this goes, for example, whether the chair dimensions were this large in the past as well,
[SPEAKER_11] considering that perhaps there were also more corpulent gentlemen representatives within the walls of the house.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, of course, when a person goes to the theater and other places,
[SPEAKER_01] of course, these kinds of benches are generally not that comfortable to sit on.
[SPEAKER_01] Here, by the way, they did everything in their power for this purpose, as there are documents to prove it,
[SPEAKER_01] that the carpenters brought sample chairs to a group of representatives.
[SPEAKER_01] There was a designated group of representatives for this.
[SPEAKER_01] So, there was a chair test?
[SPEAKER_01] Those who could sit in the various chairs in 1901–02 and then selected which one they preferred.
[SPEAKER_01] And these chairs, by the way, are folding chairs.
[SPEAKER_01] Originally, the back was made of pigskin,
[SPEAKER_01] and the chair itself is constructed with leather strips as well, so it is open in the middle, meaning we can sit on it,
[SPEAKER_01] but the air can simply circulate through it, as I mentioned earlier, so it won't get too hot.
[SPEAKER_01] However, the width of the chairs and the seating surface are indeed quite small.
[SPEAKER_01] Whether people of that era could fit into them, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01] As for documented modifications, like the one you mentioned, we know of just this one case, but it is possible that there were others before.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, so that, I mean, so that...
[SPEAKER_01] It's not comfortable, it's not meant to be, and besides, since you mentioned smoking earlier, the cigar holders in the house,
[SPEAKER_01] The cigar holders.
[SPEAKER_01] which everyone, you should imagine in many cases that during parliamentary sessions, in fact, very few people were sitting inside.
[SPEAKER_01] Everyone was out in the corridors, and that's where they talked, where the backroom deals happened.
[SPEAKER_11] They organized the Panama, as Mixa wrote about them, yes.
[SPEAKER_01] Exactly, and in fact, the more important decisions, quasi, or the actual decisions were made in the corridors.
[SPEAKER_01] It's no coincidence that these cigar holders are there, because the gentlemen really stood and sat next to them,
[SPEAKER_01] and when they rang from inside or shouted that they had to come, because there was a vote, then they put down their cigars, as you said, and went in.
[SPEAKER_01] One thing you didn't mention about the cigar holders is that the cigar slots are numbered.
[SPEAKER_01] Of course, I didn't know that. Really?
[SPEAKER_01] So when you put your cigar down, you could note that you placed it in slot 4, 18, or 7.
[SPEAKER_11] Yes, not to continue smoking your colleague's cigar.
[SPEAKER_01] These had to be kept track of. And practically, not everyone was always in the room.
[SPEAKER_01] So this also helped, in a way, that the more corpulent representatives or delegates could perhaps move around more freely during the sessions.
[SPEAKER_01] By the way, the ministerial chairs are more comfortable, those are the ones in the chest.
[SPEAKER_01] Those red armchairs are more comfortable.
[SPEAKER_11] That's why the struggle is, of course, for someone to occupy a comfortable chair, but obviously this also comes with greater responsibility, so it's not a question.
[SPEAKER_11] So in the end, just to wrap up, since we've spoken so much about the chairs, we could perhaps refer to the specific place where a given representative works and sits,
[SPEAKER_11] as we do now during the broadcast, when there isn't such a break and administrative activities and checks aren't taking place inside the house,
[SPEAKER_11] and when our dear viewers and the dear people present here don't see us, that is the workstation where a representative works, what is there around them, what supports them in carrying out their mission.
[SPEAKER_11] So, for example, what kind of card placements and so on are associated with it, how could we describe the place where a representative sits, what opportunities, tasks, duties, and equipment does it have?
[SPEAKER_01] I mean the chamber now.
[SPEAKER_01] The chamber, thank you for the clarification.
[SPEAKER_01] So in the chamber, we sit on foldable chairs, and there is also a small table, which is also foldable.
[SPEAKER_01] It is double-foldable.
[SPEAKER_01] Precisely because, if someone is about to enter the row, we lift up the table.
[SPEAKER_01] This table is not very large, so I would say a medium-sized laptop can still fit comfortably on it, but not much else.
[SPEAKER_01] The table has, where the drawer would be, actually a compartment where the representative can place a pen or anything else they want to leave there.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, it is not typical to want to leave anything there, but it is possible to store things.
[SPEAKER_01] And next to it, there is a card slot open.
[SPEAKER_01] Every representative who has voting rights has such a special card.
[SPEAKER_01] This is the card used to log into the voting machine or the voting system.
[SPEAKER_01] It is very interesting, because the plans for a voting machine actually date back to the very beginning of the 20th century, from 1907.
[SPEAKER_01] So at that time, they already tried to assist voting in some way with electrical devices.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, the system we have now was basically installed in the 2000s, if I remember correctly, in the 2000s.
[SPEAKER_01] And, if I recall correctly, on the upper right side of the representative's table, or basically everything is designed for right-handed people,
[SPEAKER_01] there is a display, a small mini monitor, I wouldn't even call it a monitor, just a small digital screen.
[SPEAKER_11] Excuse me, perhaps if someone remembers the old mobile phones, those with the small dot-matrix displays,
[SPEAKER_11] or the ones that displayed letters that way, so this is something similar, those were the first or second-generation phones.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] And in practice,
[SPEAKER_01] there are four buttons, if I remember correctly, one of which is for registering to vote, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01] Four.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, no, and abstention, these are the options.
[SPEAKER_01] And in any case, this is essentially all that a parliamentary workstation consists of, and I would also add that the table, which is the designated one, is covered with this green cloth.
[SPEAKER_11] Yes. So this is the workstation, this is the workplace where 199 people will now begin their mandates,
[SPEAKER_11] and 199 people will do so in the future.
[SPEAKER_11] In the future, they will work to implement the will that the Hungarians sent here to the house on April 12th, and to ensure that it functions this way.
[SPEAKER_11] I don't know if there is any plan, any transformation, any part of your program related to Steinlim,
[SPEAKER_11] or anything else that might happen in the future, any planned changes, any direction that might change here, whether it concerns Kossuth Square or the building itself, are you thinking about it?
[SPEAKER_01] The visible part of everything is that, if I may digress slightly, the renovation of the buildings on the opposite side of the building must be completed.
[SPEAKER_01] On the other hand, as you know, this is currently under investigation, it is entirely public, there is also a government decision on it under the Office of the Government,
[SPEAKER_01] so from the previous period, the internal modernization of the parliament building is what our company is fundamentally examining.
[SPEAKER_01] The situation here is that everyone generally faces the realization of how orderly the central parts of the building are,
[SPEAKER_01] and in fact, the staff of the Office of the Government do excellent work almost everywhere, maintaining the building every day.
[SPEAKER_01] So there is indeed a carpentry workshop, a upholstery workshop in the building, so a great deal of attention and care.
[SPEAKER_01] And I would say there is also affection from the staff of the office towards the building, after all, it is quite a great honor to work in these places.
[SPEAKER_01] And these workshops have been operating continuously since the building was handed over, and the knowledge is passed down from generation to generation.
[SPEAKER_01] I think this is a very important thing, and that is why, so to speak, the building is in such good condition.
[SPEAKER_01] However, the situation is that, well, the demands on the building have changed quite often over time.
[SPEAKER_01] To mention just the most recent example, well, the Prime Minister's Office was actually located in the building until very recently.
[SPEAKER_01] This was essentially the result of the 1950s, and naturally, after their relocation, a great deal of space became available.
[SPEAKER_01] But this led to many makeshift solutions, and these makeshift solutions are mainly found in the corridors and those areas
[SPEAKER_01] where the people who actually keep the building running on a daily basis work.
[SPEAKER_01] And I can give an example: the placement of the National Assembly's catering kitchen is far from ideal.
[SPEAKER_01] It is practically crammed into small, narrow rooms, and there is a large refrigerator, for example, that was originally for beer and canned goods.
[SPEAKER_01] So, this has probably been discontinued, but such makeshift solutions do occur, and it would be good to eliminate them,
[SPEAKER_01] not for the politicians, not for the members of parliament, but actually for the building itself, for the everyday workers and its operations,
[SPEAKER_01] to make the daily lives of the members of parliament easier and better.
[SPEAKER_01] Naturally, there are many different directions one could take, no one wants to harm the building's heritage and historical value.
[SPEAKER_01] But, well, the continuous operation of the building over the past hundred years has naturally introduced certain constraints into the whole situation.
[SPEAKER_01] And if one has the opportunity to bring a bit more order into this, then it is worth taking advantage of.
[SPEAKER_11] Is there a post office in the building?
[SPEAKER_11] Because I think there was.
[SPEAKER_11] I think it was an internal mail call.
[SPEAKER_01] Theoretically, there may not be one now.
[SPEAKER_01] I think there is a post office. That is a good name. There is a bank machine, I know that.
[SPEAKER_11] For example, is there a hairdressing service operating in the building?
[SPEAKER_01] There was a hairdressing service, but it no longer exists. There is the staff restaurant and the parliamentary restaurant, but otherwise, everyone eats together there.
[SPEAKER_01] So there isn't such a...
[SPEAKER_01] In such a radio.
[SPEAKER_01] ...deputies would be elsewhere, but everyone eats in the same space there.
[SPEAKER_01] These additional services have gradually started to disappear from the building over the past few decades, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01] And of course there is the library, which you are certainly aware of.
[SPEAKER_11] Yes, this is what I wanted to ask at the end, yes, about the library, that we could talk about the fact that theoretically all of us who have turned 18,
[SPEAKER_11] and Hungarian citizens abroad, could enroll in the library and visit the parliament to read.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, that is correct, I am not suggesting that everyone rush there now, but the library is not open at the moment.
[SPEAKER_01] I think, but this is a public library, unlike many other parliaments in the world, which are often not public libraries.
[SPEAKER_01] This one, however, is a public library, with a very good and rich collection.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't want to exaggerate, but if I remember correctly, it is the third largest library in Budapest after the National Széchenyi Library and the City Library of Ervin Szabó.
[SPEAKER_01] So many university students come here, for example, and I used to come here to study back in the day.
[SPEAKER_01] It has a very nice reading room, by the way, so it is another neo-Gothic interior space with huge bookshelves stretching two floors high, and these are accessible.
[SPEAKER_01] It is quite impressive, yes.
[SPEAKER_01] And indeed, it is a very, very quiet library, so I would add that it was really a good place to study back then.
[SPEAKER_11] That is always the best, by the way, when in a library, but I don't want to go in that direction either, but obviously the library here focuses especially on the history of parliament,
[SPEAKER_11] I suppose there are diaries, archives, and minutes available here, records of past events, which are really worth reading, I don't know who might have an interest in that,
[SPEAKER_11] but it was very good, because these minutes were kept, I don't know if they are still kept that way now, but they recorded the events as they happened.
[SPEAKER_11] This is still the case today.
[SPEAKER_11] This is still the case today? That shouts, what people say, what happens, and the most exciting parts are sometimes these interjections, the things that happen, so you don't know about them, I don't either.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, a typical such entry, about a switch lock, unrest on the right side, so there are such entries inserted into the text, and indeed, these are actually very exciting.
[SPEAKER_01] These are still recorded by parliamentary shorthand writers to this day, it was very interesting, and this had to be resolved even back in that era, there was a separate shorthand academy, shorthand school, and shorthand competitions.
[SPEAKER_01] This is a bit outdated nowadays, but in fact, they still record these sessions in this way to this day.
[SPEAKER_01] The Parliamentary Library does, yes, so it collects and digitizes documents related to Hungarian legal history, the history of Hungarian legislation, and the history of the Hungarian Parliament.
[SPEAKER_01] So, on the Parliamentary Library's website, in fact, fantastic materials are already available without the need to subscribe.
[SPEAKER_01] Among other things, for example, the original plans and the original construction documents of the parliament are accessible.
[SPEAKER_01] This building is very fortunate, and so is our work, when we think about the building and raise questions about its future or its past, it is of great help,
[SPEAKER_01] that more than 2,800 original plans are available, which were created during this 20-year construction period,
[SPEAKER_01] and more than 180,000 pages of documents related to the realization of these plans.
[SPEAKER_01] So, really all the way down to documents such as, for example, employee XY wanting to go on vacation.
[SPEAKER_11] This is the most sensational, the most exciting part in this context.
[SPEAKER_11] So, well, thank you very much for coming and for telling us about these exciting things.
[SPEAKER_11] Krisztián Kellecsényi, art historian, also told us about these things in the past.
[SPEAKER_11] Meanwhile, as we look out a bit onto the square, we are already in large numbers, more and more people are gathering, we see more and more flags, and the weather is really beautiful.
[SPEAKER_11] Those who think they might still want to go and come in person to participate in the afternoon program,
[SPEAKER_11] there is still time to arrive in abundance, we are also preparing a cultural program, a cultural program is coming.
[SPEAKER_11] Theoretically, according to our scenarios, we are already a bit behind schedule, yes, because I have a session on the history of decisions of the committee of the house scheduled for two o'clock.
[SPEAKER_11] And, of course, a proposal for a circular bill listing the ministries of Hungary,
[SPEAKER_11] for discussion with deviations from the decision-making rules, if I want to be very formal about it.
[SPEAKER_11] And after that, there will be another proposal to elevate the emergency decrees issued in light of the armed conflict on the territory of Ukraine to the level of law.
[SPEAKER_11] Such a bill will be discussed here now, which follows what is to come next, and everyone will be able to see this.
[SPEAKER_11] Then a statement to the prime minister regarding the procedure for committee hearings of ministerial candidates before their appointment, and the preparation for the next session of parliament.
[SPEAKER_11] This will be the main part; meanwhile, the colleagues are saying here that all of this will begin in about five minutes, so these will be the upcoming events.
[SPEAKER_11] And then immediately after, at three o’clock, another ceremony will begin, the election of the prime minister.
[SPEAKER_11] And the swearing-in itself. So there will be the moment when the historical flags enter with fanfares.
[SPEAKER_11] We have already seen these ceremonies several times during the morning, and the same will happen again in the afternoon.
[SPEAKER_11] In the case of a successful election, the prime minister’s solemn swearing-in and the prime minister’s speech will follow.
[SPEAKER_11] Naturally, we will also broadcast this to those who come here and think,
[SPEAKER_11] that together, I believe it can now be stated, we are in the thousands, or even tens of thousands, in number.
[SPEAKER_11] We can only see part of the square for now, and indeed, one part of the square is intentionally closed off for the military honors and the raising of the flag,
[SPEAKER_11] so it is a closed area for those visiting here, but as we saw, in the side streets all around, there are already very many people,
[SPEAKER_11] and many have come to participate in these ceremonies.
[SPEAKER_11] in the solemn ceremony, and naturally, the military ceremony will also be very impressive.
[SPEAKER_11] Colleagues have also prepared for this, with cameras everywhere, so the live broadcast on-site will be shown on large screens, with several screens on the northern and southern sides of the parliament,
[SPEAKER_11] as well as on the other side areas of the square, for those who cannot get closer to see it.
[SPEAKER_11] The broadcast can be seen well, heard well, everything on-site,
[SPEAKER_11] and naturally, everyone wants to.
[UNKNOWN] Those who think they will follow the recordings online may do so freely, and we are very much looking forward to them.
[SPEAKER_11] In fact, if they wish, they can share the link to this YouTube or Facebook live broadcast,
[SPEAKER_11] with those they know might be interested in this very beautiful and very solemn event.
[SPEAKER_11] I don't know if, in recent times, you, Krisztóf, remember such a high level of interest in the formation of the parliament.
[SPEAKER_11] I don't know what is in your memories. It is not in mine.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, of course it is not in there.
[SPEAKER_01] In the past, during the formation of new parliaments, there was not such a radical change, let us add.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't remember, for my part, that any parliamentary opening session ever generated such a level of interest.
[SPEAKER_11] Yes, so that is why we are especially pleased that so many people are here, and we can see that a great number of them are waving flags,
[SPEAKER_11] and generally the picnic atmosphere is forming and beginning, so we are gathering beautifully, and there will be quite a crowd.
[SPEAKER_11] The Prime Minister's speech, as you know, will follow after three o'clock, which we will broadcast, as I mentioned,
[SPEAKER_11] and after that, the speech, the Székely anthem, the song of joy, and the performance by the Sükösdi Danubia Tambura band will follow.
[SPEAKER_11] After that, the announcement of the expected date of the next session of parliament will follow, and then the closing of the opening session.
[SPEAKER_11] After that, we will also broadcast how the factions and the guests are leaving at a distance,
[SPEAKER_11] from the Patkó, first the guests and the two opposition factions, then Fidesz and Our Homeland will leave the Patkó during the broadcast,
[SPEAKER_11] which everyone will be able to see, and then the Tisza faction will line up inside and outside the stairs, and the program on Kossuth Square will begin,
[SPEAKER_11] which will also be a very beautiful and very elevated story.
[SPEAKER_11] Ifj. Balázs Elemér will play the piano, after which we will listen to the song "Szép vagy, Gyönyörű vagy, Magyarország,"
[SPEAKER_11] and I cannot spoil the surprise about who will be one of the main performers,
[SPEAKER_11] but obviously, it will be very dear to everyone, and Ibolya Olá will also be here, who will sing, and Karamell will also be here,
[SPEAKER_11] who will arrive with the song "Szálok a dallal," so I think it will be worth coming out to the square,
[SPEAKER_11] and it will be worth participating in person. This is a historical moment, to take photos and then to tell the story afterwards.
[SPEAKER_11] I was there too, and I also participated in these events.
[SPEAKER_11] So this will be the program here, and of course there will be an opportunity to get a bit closer,
[SPEAKER_11] after the military honors are completed, and when Péter Magyar comes down, there will be an opportunity, as far as I know,
[SPEAKER_11] as far as I know, to meet them, well, even if not directly, but to get close and meet
[SPEAKER_11] everyone at the steps of the parliament, the candidates, I still reflexively say the number when I call them candidates,
[SPEAKER_11] but please forgive me for this mistake, as it is the day of transition, and from tomorrow onward, I am sure,
[SPEAKER_11] we will all be better at this, as we will already be able to call them officially as representatives.
[SPEAKER_11] We will get through this period with fewer language slips, which is coming later, for now still, and well, of course they are no longer candidates,
[SPEAKER_11] since they are officially representatives now, as we just witnessed and saw these oaths of office,
[SPEAKER_11] and we saw the speeches, we saw everything that was broadcast here.
[SPEAKER_11] So thank you very much, Kristóf, thank you to you as well, you now know a lot, that you were here,
[SPEAKER_11] and of course, as I mentioned briefly, the historical flag procession, which was also mentioned,
[SPEAKER_11] is an interesting gesture of this ceremonial series and tradition that is taking place,
[SPEAKER_11] so in addition to the special fanfares, those who have just tuned in via the broadcast will be able to see this,
[SPEAKER_11] those who have been with us for a long time have also seen it before, how it looks when these flags march in,
[SPEAKER_11] these historical flags, which have been part of Hungarian military, state, and local celebrations since 1985,
[SPEAKER_11] so these flag processions, by the way, or this flag procession displays the most characteristic flag types of Hungarian military history,
[SPEAKER_11] or the flags associated with the most famous periods of Hungarian military history.
[SPEAKER_11] Now, just briefly without aiming for completeness, but visible there inside is the flag of the chieftain from the conquest period,
[SPEAKER_11] a reconstructed version of Saint Stephen's flag is also visible.
[SPEAKER_11] The Árpád dynasty royal flag from the end of the 12th century, which is a red flag with a small pointed stripe and a cross on it,
[SPEAKER_11] the family flag of the Árpád kings, the Anjou royal flag, the flag of John Hunyadi,
[SPEAKER_11] the flag of King Matthias's Black Army with the lions holding the crown,
[SPEAKER_11] with black stripes in the middle on a blue background, I don't know, they call this a coat of arms, I suppose it has a coat of arms, and also with the black lions,
[SPEAKER_11] but the flag of the hero of Szigetvár, Miklós Zrínyi, also enters among the historical flags,
[SPEAKER_11] who, well, how can I put it, so that if anyone has done anything, then he certainly did a great deal to ensure that Hungary exists today,
[SPEAKER_11] in this form, and of course the later relative and writer of the Zrínyi story,
[SPEAKER_11] who beautifully preserved the story and memory of the earlier hero, the earlier relative, and his verses, just those that come to mind now,
[SPEAKER_11] this is not written with a pennant, with a black tent, but let me make it vivid, let me stain it with the blood of the enemy, so that my eternal fame may be, as he once put it in that old classic,
[SPEAKER_11] and somehow, at least for me, it echoes a little onto today, because perhaps a little,
[UNKNOWN] today will also be such a day, just thinking of Zrínyi, all of this comes to mind, that we will perhaps all engrave this story into our hearts for a long time,
[SPEAKER_11] and to follow such a significant, such a fundamental change in Hungarian society on the pages of history books,
[SPEAKER_11] to be here in person, to document it, to be a part of it, whether by going to vote or by voluntarily participating in the campaign,
[SPEAKER_11] and here we see how many people are already here, this is really slowly approaching a full house, there is still room, so it is possible to come,
[SPEAKER_11] the pictures shown by the colleagues from above are beautiful, and of course the most beautiful pictures are here,
[SPEAKER_11] when we see the smiling faces after the beautiful buildings, and welcome everyone who has just arrived here,
[SPEAKER_11] it is of course also possible to follow what will happen in the National Assembly while solving crossword puzzles.
[SPEAKER_11] This was just a quick aside, the flag of Miklós Zrínyi is also coming, really just without aiming for completeness,
[SPEAKER_11] but the flag of Gabriel Bethlen, the Transylvanian prince from 1617, will also be brought in, so we will also see that.
[SPEAKER_11] Just to show how serious historical predecessors we are standing on now, so what is happening in Hungary today is not without any background.
[SPEAKER_11] So, the historical heroes we remember, we recall, whose work, life, and efforts are symbolized,
[SPEAKER_11] These flags, the fact that they are present at such an event, certainly adds to the feeling that we can sense how much historical weight all of what is happening here today carries.
[SPEAKER_11] So I think this is definitely a very beautiful gesture.
[SPEAKER_11] We will see István Bocskai, Hajdú of Szalonta, and the Officer.
[SPEAKER_11] And this is the flag, where, incidentally, a black eagle and a golden lion are fighting against each other on the flag.
[SPEAKER_11] But the flag of the Nemesi Uprising in Nyitra County from the 1660s will also be here.
[SPEAKER_11] The flag of Prince Imre Thököly will also be visible when these historical flags are paraded in.
[SPEAKER_11] And, of course, the flag of Prince Rákóczi as well.
[SPEAKER_11] And, of course, Prince Rákóczi's motto is cum Deo pro patria libertate, with God for the homeland, for freedom.
[SPEAKER_11] A large inscription, a great legendary memory.
[SPEAKER_11] Or, of course, one of the smaller flags belonged to Miklós Zrínyi.
[SPEAKER_11] But I think the inscription on his ship, the Szorczbón, was Nihil, Good luck, nothing else,
[SPEAKER_11] which is also connected or related to it.
[SPEAKER_11] But here, among the historical flags, there will be a kuruc cavalry flag from Rákóczi's time,
[SPEAKER_11] a cavalry flag from 1706.
[SPEAKER_11] And the Baranya Hussar Regiment's flag.
[SPEAKER_11] The cavalry flag of the Nemesi Uprising in Pest County from the 1730s.
[SPEAKER_11] The flag of the Jászkun or Török Hussar Regiment from the 1770s.
[SPEAKER_11] The cavalry flag of the Nemesi Uprising in Pest County from the end of the 18th century.
[SPEAKER_11] And they are bringing all of these.
[SPEAKER_11] But the 1849 Honvéd cavalry flag after the defeat at Tápiószentmiklós will also be here.
[SPEAKER_17] [SPEAKER_17] Which also evokes the memory of the 1848 revolution here in the parliament.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] The Hungarian Royal Honvéd flag, introduced in 1869, is also visible.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] And with this, we also evoke the era of the Compromise, which, well, the era of the Compromise and the era of dualism is,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] the era that this building, which we are standing in front of, is one of the largest, one of the most monumental achievements of that time and of that cooperation.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] And perhaps it is also proof of what it is like when we try to operate a community, a state organization,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] in such a way that yes, there are our differences, quite significant differences, even such differences that could lead to revolution,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] but if the leaders who are meant to lead the people learn to communicate well in the language of politics and diplomacy,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] then they can greatly contribute to the fact that while we have our debates and differences of opinion,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] we can still have results and the country can grow, which, as we know, contributed during the era of dualism to the emergence of,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] a civil society layer,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] which arose in Hungary and entered Hungarian history as one of its most flourishing periods,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] and let’s not even speak of the far-reaching effects this had on culture,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] and I do not want to open up the discussion about how the appearance of the Western magazine was no coincidence, how it could happen then,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] with its launch in 1908 and, as we know, it was probably withdrawn in 1941, I think,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] perhaps this was connected to the death of Mihály Babics, if I remember correctly,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] but I am not certain about this,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] definitely up to the hundreds, if I am wrong, I apologize for it.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] So, these are the eras that proved everything: that if we sit down at the negotiation table,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] we can talk to each other, we have common goals, then for the sake of a people, for the sake of a country, we can indeed do something.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] As Ágnes Forstófer, in my opinion, very sympathetically and very rightly said in her welcoming speech all of that,
[SPEAKER_11] that she also sees this and considers it one of the most important tasks,
[UNKNOWN] that a serious, fact-based, scholarly dialogue indeed emerges,
[SPEAKER_11] and that the work based on this will also take place within these walls.
[SPEAKER_11] I will just quickly mention a few flags, just to truly convey the sense of completeness,
[SPEAKER_11] how many different historical periods are represented here, when these events take place within these walls.
[SPEAKER_11] They bring in the Hungarian Royal Honvéd cavalry flag standardized in 1938,
[SPEAKER_11] but the 1949-pattern unit flag, as it is called, also appears there,
[SPEAKER_11] and essentially, the original version of the flag used by the insurgents in the 1956 revolution also appears in this house.
[SPEAKER_11] Indeed, this was the defining symbol of the 1956 revolution, the Kossuth coat of arms and the torn red, white, green flag,
[SPEAKER_11] and the flag with the Rákosi coat of arms, that is, the western-style red, white, green flag with the Rákosi coat of arms,
[SPEAKER_11] the Hungarian flag was completely alien to Hungarian traditions, and the demonstrators had already torn out the symbol of the dictatorship from the flag on the first day of the revolution,
[SPEAKER_11] and yes, they decided that this torn flag would be the one under which we would line up as one people, and indeed, we would decide in favor of change.
[SPEAKER_11] So, this is where we stand now, Ladies and Gentlemen, on this beautiful May day.
[SPEAKER_11] We have had a very beautiful morning so far, I think the time so far has been very useful,
[SPEAKER_11] and what is yet to come, that is, that I have already stirred everyone up so much with these flags,
[SPEAKER_11] and I am not saying that I will ask for these pieces of information, but if anyone wishes to discuss it, we will gladly be available.
[SPEAKER_11] So, we are now very well prepared regarding the flags, and I believe we will all engrave all these events into our memories, our minds, and our hearts,
[SPEAKER_11] which await us in the days to come.
[SPEAKER_11] Because for those who have just joined, they have been informed,
[SPEAKER_11] and I say that the election of the Prime Minister will follow shortly.
[SPEAKER_11] Peter Magyar will also give a speech within the house, which we will broadcast.
[SPEAKER_11] On-site, of course, this can also be followed here and will be audible here on-site.
[SPEAKER_11] It was good to see, while Ágnes Forsthofer was speaking, that everyone stopped, everyone looked at the screens respectfully, kindly, curiously, and with smiles.
[SPEAKER_11] and just as the members of parliament and the parliamentary candidates inside the house did,
[SPEAKER_11] those gathered here outside also expressed their approval, support, and sympathy with applause.
[SPEAKER_11] And already inside the house, as I see it, Forsthofer Ágnes is at the back, as if András Kulja is standing there, and from the right I think Gabriella Gerzsényi is being halved by her hairstyle.
[SPEAKER_11] Dóra Dávid and Eszter Lakos are currently walking across the screen, so they are with the Tisza European Anthem,
[SPEAKER_11] the various parliamentary representatives are also here naturally at this beautiful event,
[SPEAKER_11] and since Kollár Kinka is being covered by András Kulja, and here Georgy Velkei is just uniting with Peter Magyar from behind, if I recognized him correctly.
[SPEAKER_11] So the preparations for the next agenda item are already underway within the walls of the house,
[SPEAKER_11] and naturally, after Peter Magyar delivers his speech and takes the oath, we will listen to the anthems we usually listen to, and they will come out.
[SPEAKER_11] By the way, here is Peter Magyar's family, his sons, his father, visible with whom Ágnes Forsthofer is speaking right now.
[SPEAKER_11] Meanwhile, outside on the square, the peaceful hugging group is resting in safety.
[SPEAKER_11] I cannot determine the dog's breed, but it seems like a housing estate mix at first glance.
[SPEAKER_11] But in any case, we are glad they brought it, because I think it is a family event,
[SPEAKER_11] and that we all participate in this event with joy, in safety, and in good spirits, is one of the guarantees that
[SPEAKER_11] everyone wants, that everyone wants.
[SPEAKER_17] This is one of the guests seen via the broadcast here at Kossuth Square today.
[SPEAKER_11] If someone is following the broadcast online, I know I have mentioned it several times already, but please share it, send it,
[SPEAKER_11] to others as well, to friends as well, the more people who see it, the better.
[SPEAKER_11] Well, it is a big commitment for Tiszó, if I may use this expression, to operate much more transparently
[SPEAKER_11] than what we have seen and experienced over the past 16 years.
[SPEAKER_11] Politics seems to have hidden away, withdrawn
[SPEAKER_11] behind grand stone buildings and decisions were made about us in smoky cigar rooms,
[SPEAKER_11] and in many cases, without the Hungarian people.
[SPEAKER_11] And now this moment has arrived, when transparency is moving back in.
[SPEAKER_11] And the fact that we are here today, and so many of us are here in this area, is also one of the symbols of
[SPEAKER_11] how differently Tiszó envisions the country we will live in together in the future.
[SPEAKER_11] The fact that a little girl can wave and fly the flag
[SPEAKER_11] with a small red flag, a red-white-green flag, safely around her father's neck,
[SPEAKER_11] is an important thing, that someone is already here at such a young age, and will be able to tell about
[SPEAKER_11] what it was like to be here, and what it was like to listen to these conversations,
[SPEAKER_11] and how nice it is to smile so kindly in the photo.
[SPEAKER_11] Because this makes all of us feel a little better, while in the rows of parliamentary seats, István Kapitány,
[SPEAKER_11] not that I would say he is burdened with worries,
[SPEAKER_11] but as I see it, is a bit excitedly waiting to see what will happen in the future.
[SPEAKER_11] Tiszó's deputy leader, Márk Radnai, and Andrea Rost, who will work in government commissioner positions in the future.
[SPEAKER_11] Andrea Rost, as you know, will continue the cultural mission of Hungarian music in the future,
[SPEAKER_11] and Márk Radnai will lead an institution as a government commissioner, which will work,
[SPEAKER_11] which will bring together a story that asks, what is a government commissioner,
[SPEAKER_11] the possibility of forming a social unity, a social dialogue,
[SPEAKER_11] which will certainly guarantee that in the future in Hungary,
[SPEAKER_11] decisions will not be made without the Hungarian people, and that indeed that voice, indeed that idea,
[SPEAKER_11] those visions that emerge among the citizens of Hungary, around the citizens, on the streets, in the homes,
[SPEAKER_11] in conversations, yes, in the corner pubs, in the public spaces, about which they talk,
[SPEAKER_11] will indeed be represented.
[SPEAKER_11] And they will be heard within these walls, indeed taking on a form, indeed a dialogue will emerge,
[SPEAKER_11] which will lead to these voices becoming part of the legislative process.
[UNKNOWN] And indeed, let all of this function as many of us imagined it would after the regime change.
[SPEAKER_11] We are expecting that everything that happens within these walls will be public.
[SPEAKER_11] We are currently somewhat behind schedule, but this does not deter us in the slightest.
[SPEAKER_11] I believe that we will remain steadfast.
[SPEAKER_11] This slogan of tonight will not be forgotten, the one that was already spoken, this "Let There Be Dance,"
[SPEAKER_11] which will likely begin after five o'clock.
[SPEAKER_11] Then, in the form of a DJ set, I think the appropriate rhythms will provide us with the opportunity,
[SPEAKER_11] to properly celebrate that revolutionary people's festival, which belongs to all of us.
[SPEAKER_11] We also thank those who have already arrived, and I see, many of you are wearing Tisza t-shirts, Tisza volunteer vests.
[SPEAKER_11] They are the ones who were the engines, the souls of the regime change, who carried, transported,
[SPEAKER_11] spread the clear message, went door-to-door, so we very much thank them for their work from here as well.
[SPEAKER_11] I think they deserve a huge round of applause, because it was this work that ensured that,
[UNKNOWN] that during the country tour, those Tisza representatives, Tisza political aspirants, who were then still aspirants
[SPEAKER_11] are able to carry out this regime change, and indeed are able to work so that at those locations,
[SPEAKER_11] when someone arrived somewhere, or someone set out somewhere, they would know that the message they conveyed would indeed arrive properly.
[SPEAKER_11] Ágnes Forstóffer has taken her seat, so we will now hand over the floor to the parliament,
[SPEAKER_11] and another exciting segment follows in today’s wonderful day.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly! It is a great honor to greet you for the first time from the Podium. We continue our work!
[SPEAKER_13] I request the secretaries Sóti, Anikó, Zsuzsa, Anna, and Gábor Varga to assist me in presiding over the session.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly! In my capacity as Chairperson, I have submitted a proposal in order for the National Assembly to discuss, deviating from the standing orders,
[SPEAKER_13] the Téper 7 topic on the listing of ministries of Hungary.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly! I draw your attention to the fact that a two-thirds majority of the present members is required to deviate from the standing orders.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask the Honorable National Assembly whether it accepts the discussion of the Téper 7 bill deviating from the standing orders. Please vote now!
[SPEAKER_13] The National Assembly accepted the deviation from the standing orders with 187 yes votes, 6 no votes, and without abstentions.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly! In my capacity as Chairperson, I have submitted a proposal in order for the National Assembly to discuss, deviating from the standing orders,
[SPEAKER_13] the Téper 8 bill on elevating to the legal level the state of emergency decrees issued in view of the armed conflict on the territory of Ukraine.
[SPEAKER_13] The proposal is available on the website.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly! I draw your attention to the fact that a two-thirds majority of the present members is required to deviate from the standing orders.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask the Honorable National Assembly! Does it accept the discussion of the Téper 8 bill deviating from the standing orders? Please vote now!
[SPEAKER_13] The National Assembly accepted the deviation from the standing orders with 187 yes votes and 6 no votes.
[SPEAKER_13] The Honorable National Assembly accepted the deviation from the standing orders with 187 yes votes and 6 no votes, without abstentions.
[SPEAKER_13] Next in order is the decision on the amendment proposal submitted to the Téper 7 bill on the listing of ministries of Hungary, and the final vote.
[SPEAKER_13] I would like to inform you that the proposer submitted an amendment proposal under number Téper 7-1.
[SPEAKER_13] An amendment proposal was submitted under number Téper 7.
[SPEAKER_13] We will first make a decision on this.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask the Honorable National Assembly whether it accepts the amendment proposal numbered Téper 7-1.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask you to vote now!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13] The National Assembly rejected it with 196 yes votes and no abstentions.
[SPEAKER_13] The amendment proposal was accepted.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask the Honorable National Assembly whether it accepts the amended bill numbered Téper 7-1.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask you to vote now!
[UNKNOWN] The National Assembly rejected it with 96 yes votes and no abstentions.
[UNKNOWN] An amendment proposal was submitted.
[UNKNOWN] I ask the Honorable National Assembly whether it accepts the amended bill numbered Téper 7-1.
[UNKNOWN] I ask you to vote now!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13] The National Assembly rejected it with 96 yes votes and no abstentions.
[SPEAKER_13] The amendment proposal was accepted with 141 yes votes, 2 no votes, and 53 abstentions.
[SPEAKER_13] In view of the armed conflict on the territory of Ukraine, the final vote on the bill numbered Téper 8 regarding the elevation of emergency decrees to the level of law.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask the Honorable National Assembly whether it accepts the amended bill numbered Téper 7-1.
[SPEAKER_13] Kérdezem a tisztelt Országgyűlést, elfogadja-e a Téper 7-1 számú módosult törvényjavaslat.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask you to vote now.
[SPEAKER_13] The National Assembly adopted the bill with 190 votes in favor, 6 against, and no abstentions.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly!
[SPEAKER_13] Next on the agenda is the decision on the proposal regarding the establishment of committees of the National Assembly and the election of their members and officers.
[SPEAKER_13] I make my proposal regarding the committee system, the members of the committees, and the officers in accordance with the agreement of the faction leaders.
[SPEAKER_13] The proposal also includes my suggestion regarding the name of the committee representing national minorities, as well as the person of its chair and vice-chairs.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly!
[SPEAKER_13] I would like to inform you that today, in the committees on defense, public safety, national security, and foreign affairs, we can only elect members for whom the national security check has already been completed; the election of the remaining members will take place at a later date.
[SPEAKER_13] Taking into account that, according to the provisions of the National Assembly Act, we must make a separate decision on the person of the chair of the legislative committee,
[SPEAKER_13] we first decide on the committee system, the officers and members of the committees, and only after that will we vote on the chair of the legislative committee.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask the Honorable National Assembly whether, in accordance with proposal HPR 6, it establishes its committee system and elects the officers and members of the committees, with the exception of the chair of the legislative committee.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask you to vote now!
[UNKNOWN] I ask the Honorable National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_13] Honored Members of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_13]
[SPEAKER_13] Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_13] I wish you productive and successful work.
[SPEAKER_13] Honored National Assembly, the next item is the election of the Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_13] Based on paragraph F of the second paragraph of Article 1,
[SPEAKER_13] and the third paragraph of Article 16 of the Fundamental Law, Dr. Tamás Sulyog, President of the Republic,
[SPEAKER_13] has nominated Hungarian Péter as Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_13] The relevant proposal can be accessed on the IT network under number S-12.
[SPEAKER_13] Honored National Assembly, according to the fourth paragraph of Article 16 of the Fundamental Law,
[SPEAKER_13] the election of the Prime Minister requires the votes of more than half of the members of the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_13] The Prime Minister assumes office upon election.
[SPEAKER_13] I call upon the Honored National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_13] Shall Hungarian Péter be elected as Prime Minister of Hungary?
[SPEAKER_13] I ask you to vote now!
[SPEAKER_13] I shall announce the decision.
[SPEAKER_13] The National Assembly voted 140 in favor, 54 against, and 1 abstention.
[SPEAKER_13] Hungarian Péter was elected Prime Minister of Hungary.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly! The solemn oath-taking is now to follow.
[SPEAKER_13] I ask you to stand up as we pay respects before the national flag and the historical flags are brought in.
[SPEAKER_04] Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_05] Honorable National Assembly! The solemn oath-taking is now to follow.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly! The solemn oath-taking is now to follow.
[UNKNOWN] Honorable National Assembly! The solemn oath-taking is now to follow.
[SPEAKER_16] I, Hungarian Péter, do hereby pledge to remain loyal to Hungary and to its fundamental law.
[SPEAKER_00] I shall uphold its laws and ensure that others do as well.
[SPEAKER_00] I shall exercise the office of Prime Minister for the benefit of the Hungarian nation.
[SPEAKER_16] I shall exercise the office of Prime Minister for the benefit of the Hungarian nation.
[SPEAKER_16] God help me!
[UNKNOWN] God help me!
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable National Assembly! I now ask Mr. Mihály Balogh, Member of Parliament, to prepare the oath documents for signing.
[SPEAKER_13] I also ask Mr. Hungarian Péter, Prime Minister, to sign them with his signature.
[UNKNOWN] I also ask Mr. Hungarian Péter, Prime Minister, to sign them with his signature.
[UNKNOWN] I also ask the Prime Minister to sign them with his signature.
[SPEAKER_13] Mr. Prime Minister, on behalf of myself, I sincerely congratulate you on the parliamentary elections.
[SPEAKER_13] Mr. Prime Minister, on my behalf, I sincerely congratulate you on the parliamentary elections.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable colleagues! I would like to inform you that Mr. Prime Minister will receive the congratulations in the center of the chamber, first from Dr. Tamás Sulyog, President of the Republic.
[UNKNOWN] He will receive the congratulations in the center of the delegation, first from Dr. Tamás Sulyog, President of the Republic.
[UNKNOWN] In the center of the delegation, he will receive the congratulations, first from Dr. Tamás Sulyog, in the center of the delegation, he will receive the congratulations, first from Dr. Tamás Sulyog, in the center of the delegation, he will receive the congratulations, first from Dr. Tamás Sulyog, in the center of the delegation, he will receive the congratulations, first from Dr. Tamás Sulyog, in the center of the delegation, he will receive the congratulations, first from Dr. Tamás Sulyog, in the center of the delegation, he will receive the congratulations, first from Dr. Tamás Sulyog, in the center of the delegation, he will receive the congratulations, first from Dr. Tamás Sulyog.
[UNKNOWN] Honorable fellow citizens, Hungarians, both within and beyond the borders,
[UNKNOWN] honored guests, honored colleagues!
[UNKNOWN] In this festive moment, I stand before you with emotion.
[SPEAKER_16] I have just sworn an oath to serve our wonderful country, Hungary, to serve a nation
[UNKNOWN] whose first Prime Minister was Count Lajos Batthyány, who was deposed at Martonvásár.
[SPEAKER_16] Just as 36 years ago,
[SPEAKER_16] in 1990,
[SPEAKER_16] in these very halls, the late Prime Minister József Antall recalled
[SPEAKER_16] the fate of Count Lajos Batthyány and Pál Teleki,
[SPEAKER_16] and later, Prime Minister Imre Nagy's martyr's death for the nation,
[SPEAKER_16] serves as a warning for every Prime Minister of Hungary,
[SPEAKER_16] and is an eternal symbol of Hungarian history.
[SPEAKER_16] Therefore, our predecessors gave their lives for the nation,
[SPEAKER_16] sacrificing their lives.
[SPEAKER_16] Being the Prime Minister of Hungary carries a great political and human responsibility.
[SPEAKER_16] But it also carries a historical burden,
[UNKNOWN] that their sacrifice, the sacrifice of millions, made for the nation,
[UNKNOWN] must not, cannot be in vain.
[UNKNOWN] With faith, with willpower,
[SPEAKER_16] with love for the homeland, I will work every day of the year,
[SPEAKER_16] every hour of the day, in order
[SPEAKER_16] to live up to the warning example set by predecessors such as
[SPEAKER_16] Lajos Battyányi, Imre Nagy, or even József Antall.
[SPEAKER_16] Integrity, courage, wisdom.
[SPEAKER_16] As Prime Minister, with due humility, I will take example from them,
[SPEAKER_16] and learn from them.
[SPEAKER_16] I feel and understand my responsibility.
[SPEAKER_16] I have seen the fate of my predecessors,
[UNKNOWN] and not only that of the heroes.
[SPEAKER_16] I have also seen how the position of Prime Minister
[SPEAKER_16] can be placed in the service of power instead of the service of the nation.
[SPEAKER_16] I have seen how power can slowly crush people beneath it.
[SPEAKER_16] how a politician can gradually become a prisoner of their own system,
[SPEAKER_16] and how a political community can lose its connection with the people
[SPEAKER_16] from whom it originally received its mandate.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungarian history is a warning for every prime minister.
[SPEAKER_16] A warning that power is transient.
[SPEAKER_16] However, the consequences of our decisions remain with us for generations.
[SPEAKER_16] A country can be lifted up by a few brave and honest decisions,
[UNKNOWN] but it can also be destroyed by selfishness, arrogance, short-sightedness, or even mediocrity.
[SPEAKER_16] That is why I would like to clearly state here, in the house of Hungarian democracy and constitutionalism,
[SPEAKER_16] that I will not rule Hungary, I will serve my country.
[SPEAKER_16] The words of József Antall set the moral standard and duty for this service for us.
[SPEAKER_16] I will serve as long as my service is useful.
[UNKNOWN] I do this to the best of my knowledge, as long as I can and as long as the Hungarian nation demands it.
[UNKNOWN] I am not standing here because I am somehow special or superior to anyone else in the country. I am not.
[UNKNOWN] I am standing here because millions of Hungarians have decided they want change.
[SPEAKER_16] And this trust we have received is both an honor, a serious moral responsibility, and a wonderful feeling.
[SPEAKER_16] A wonderful feeling, because working for this country is uplifting.
[SPEAKER_16] There is no other place in the world where so much talent, so much perseverance, so much pain, and so much will to live have converged in the history of a single nation.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungary is wonderful because it has repeatedly been able to rise again.
[SPEAKER_16] Even when many had already given up on it.
[SPEAKER_16] Because in this country, millions of people work quietly and with dignity, day after day, for their families, their communities, and their beloved homeland.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungary is our homeland, which can be heartbreakingly sad and at the same time infinitely joyful.
[SPEAKER_16] Our homeland is full of hardship.
[SPEAKER_16] Joy, humor, ingenuity, yearning for freedom, and love of country.
[SPEAKER_16] Our homeland, our fate, the future of our children and grandchildren.
[SPEAKER_16] Fellow countrymen, in the history of the Third Hungarian Republic, the strength with which the Hungarian people have stood on the side of change is unprecedented.
[SPEAKER_16] On April 12, 2026.
[SPEAKER_16] The number of people who participated in the parliamentary election was unprecedented, just as the 3,385,000 votes for change were.
[SPEAKER_16] Unprecedented is the path that Hungary, the Hungarian people, have taken in the past two years.
[SPEAKER_16] I thank them!
[SPEAKER_16] Thank you to everyone present within the walls of the National Assembly, or as its designer Imre Steindl called it, the temple of the constitution, for hearing and understanding this will.
[UNKNOWN] The Hungarian people have given us the mandate to end decades of drifting.
[SPEAKER_16] They have given us the mandate to open a new chapter.
[SPEAKER_16] Do you know that we are to change not only the government, but the system?
[UNKNOWN] To start anew.
[SPEAKER_16] We must know, however, that there is no starting anew without reconciliation.
[SPEAKER_16] Reconciliation, however, is not possible without justice.
[SPEAKER_16] Justice, in turn, is not possible without facing the truth.
[SPEAKER_16] We need to face the truth, seek justice, achieve reconciliation, and start anew.
[SPEAKER_16] If any of these elements are missing for the Hungarian people who have entrusted us with authority, they must be disappointed once again.
[SPEAKER_16] Honorable colleagues!
[SPEAKER_16] We need to face the facts.
[SPEAKER_16] Symbolically.
[SPEAKER_16] because the two prime ministers who gave their names to the Orbán-Gyurcsány era are not sitting here today in the rows of benches,
[SPEAKER_16] to openly and clearly speak about the legacy they have left behind.
[SPEAKER_16] Not simply because their parties lost the election,
[SPEAKER_16] but because they failed politically, personally, and morally.
[SPEAKER_16] The political system failed,
[SPEAKER_16] which constantly fed off each other,
[SPEAKER_16] even looted the country,
[SPEAKER_16] mobilized people against one another,
[SPEAKER_16] while depleting Hungary’s economic, moral, and social reserves.
[SPEAKER_16] Twenty-two years after Hungary received the greatest opportunity in its modern history through EU accession,
[SPEAKER_16] our beloved homeland has already become a scorched earth.
[UNKNOWN] It was looted, plundered, betrayed, and misled.
[SPEAKER_16] And when they should take responsibility for all this,
[SPEAKER_16] they run away from their own political community and the country, resign,
[UNKNOWN] withdraw, and wash their hands.
[UNKNOWN] The fact that they are not sitting here today is a precise reflection of this political culture.
[SPEAKER_16] which has ruled this country for decades,
[UNKNOWN] of responsibility avoidance, the complete lack of self-examination
[SPEAKER_16] and power exercised without consequences.
[SPEAKER_16] But the Hungarian people, dear colleagues,
[SPEAKER_16] will not do the favor of allowing this confrontation to be avoided.
[SPEAKER_16] We inherited a country where three million people live in poverty,
[SPEAKER_16] 800,000 pensioners below the minimum subsistence level,
[SPEAKER_16] 400,000 children growing up in deprivation and social exclusion.
[SPEAKER_16] We inherited a country where the outgoing government managed to accumulate
[SPEAKER_16] more than 90 percent of the annual planned budget deficit in just three months.
[SPEAKER_16] Where power failed, and the failed power, even in its final hours,
[SPEAKER_16] tried to steal everything that was movable.
[UNKNOWN] We inherited a country where tens of thousands of people die prematurely every year because
[SPEAKER_16] the healthcare system was bled dry.
[SPEAKER_16] Where 900,000 people do not have their own family doctor.
[SPEAKER_16] Where one has to wait weeks or years for an examination or a surgery,
[SPEAKER_16] and where people live five years less than the European average.
[UNKNOWN] We inherited a country where education has become, not a means of upward mobility,
[SPEAKER_16] but increasingly a tool for the reproduction of social inequalities.
[SPEAKER_16] Where a child's fate is often already determined at the moment of birth by the family's financial situation and place of residence.
[UNKNOWN] We inherited a country where half of adult Hungarians try to live on less than 300,000 forints,
[SPEAKER_16] while prices have spiraled out of control and our money has lost nearly half its value,
[SPEAKER_16] and housing has become an unattainable luxury for hundreds of thousands of young families.
[UNKNOWN] We inherited a country where child protection left many people,
[UNKNOWN] often leaving the most vulnerable children completely alone,
[SPEAKER_16] and where countless young people had to grow up, or still have to grow up, in fear, humiliation, or without love,
[SPEAKER_16] in institutions that were supposed to provide them with safety.
[SPEAKER_16] We inherited a country,
[SPEAKER_16] where the state promoted the enrichment of a narrow political and economic elite instead of its own citizens, while trillions,
[SPEAKER_16] Trillions disappeared from foundations, from the National Bank, through overpriced and unnecessary investments and political,
[SPEAKER_16] into the pockets of various client groups in Hungary.
[SPEAKER_16] We inherited a Hungary that has become the most corrupt member state of the European Union,
[SPEAKER_16] and where the wealth siphoned off, stolen from the common service of the Hungarian nation over the past one and a half decades is estimated at 20,000 billion forints,
[SPEAKER_16] from the pockets of the Hungarian people.
[SPEAKER_16] From the pockets of the Hungarian people.
[UNKNOWN] From the pockets of the Hungarian people.
[SPEAKER_16] From the tables of Hungarian children and the elderly.
[SPEAKER_16] A country where 8,000 billion forints in EU funds became inaccessible due to corruption and the deliberate dismantling of the rule of law.
[SPEAKER_16] This is the money of the Hungarian people, from which hospitals, schools, roads, and businesses could have developed.
[UNKNOWN] This is the money of the Hungarian people, from which hospitals, schools, roads, and businesses could have developed.
[SPEAKER_16] We inherited a country where politics deliberately turned Hungarians against Hungarians.
[SPEAKER_16] they lost their faith in the idea that this country could still be a fair, humane, and shared homeland for all Hungarians.
[SPEAKER_16] Fellow citizens, for the politics of the past two decades, with the exception of a narrow power elite, the entire country paid a heavy price.
[SPEAKER_16] Our emotionally Fidesz-aligned compatriots, the voters of our homeland, the left-wing voters, and even those who, disillusioned, turned their backs on politics—also paid a price.
[SPEAKER_16] Let us state clearly: what happened was not the fault of the Hungarian people.
[SPEAKER_16] The Hungarian people have just proven that, in contrast to their leaders,
[UNKNOWN] this country is capable of renewal, capable of reason, capable of expressing the desire and demand for freedom and justice.
[SPEAKER_16] The Hungarian nation, often described and blamed by scientists, journalists, and opinion-makers, is far wiser, far more democratic.
[SPEAKER_16] Far more patriotic than its own political elite, which has betrayed it over the past decades.
[SPEAKER_16] While the right and left-wing politics kept each other in check, they also sustained one another.
[SPEAKER_16] While continuously mobilizing their own factions against each other, in reality, they mutually maintained each other's political system.
[SPEAKER_16] Every political side must confront its own responsibility.
[SPEAKER_16] Former ruling party representatives and the Fidesz power elite will have a long way to go toward this confrontation.
[SPEAKER_16] This confrontation will only take its first step when it is acknowledged that their leaders caused
[SPEAKER_16] such damage, both personally and in a moral sense.
[SPEAKER_16] The true confrontation will come when the question can also be raised: how the civic right wing, the former civic right wing, allowed this damage to occur.
[SPEAKER_16] that former opposition, which has fallen out of the National Assembly, also has to account for the fact
[SPEAKER_16] that it often considered its own political survival more important than the future of the country.
[SPEAKER_16] Democracy was not dismantled by the former opposition, but for many years it was content with an opposition role without consequences,
[SPEAKER_16] while our country drifted deeper and deeper into an ever more serious crisis.
[SPEAKER_16] The Hungarian people do not deserve such an elite.
[UNKNOWN] They do not deserve such a politics as has been handed to them in the past few decades.
[SPEAKER_16] Therefore, the members of TISZA pledge to close that historical era which repeatedly pitted Hungarians against each other.
[SPEAKER_16] We undertake a joint commitment that Hungary will once again become a stronger country, one in which the Hungarian people can take pride,
[SPEAKER_16] but what unites us will be stronger than what divides us.
[SPEAKER_16] That we will once again learn to think of ourselves as a nation,
[SPEAKER_16] even if we come from different places, carry different experiences, or voted for different political communities.
[SPEAKER_16] We pledge that in the coming years, we will strengthen the language of trust, humanity, and shared patriotism in this country.
[SPEAKER_16] That public life will once again be permeated by cooperation, curiosity, mutual respect, and a sense of shared responsibility.
[SPEAKER_16] That Hungary will finally become a common home for every Hungarian, where everyone can feel they have a place in the nation.
[SPEAKER_16] We pledge that we will respect the dignity of every Hungarian.
[SPEAKER_16] The dignity of those who supported us, and the dignity of those who believed in another political community.
[SPEAKER_16] Because belonging to the nation is a shared fate,
[SPEAKER_16] a shared language, a shared story, and a shared responsibility.
[SPEAKER_16] We pledge to build a country where politics is once again able to give people hope, security, and shared goals.
[SPEAKER_16] A Hungary where families, friends, and communities are once again able to talk to one another,
[SPEAKER_16] to listen to one another and to rejoice together in belonging to the same country.
[SPEAKER_16] And we also pledge that at every decision we make, we will remember that historical moment,
[SPEAKER_16] when millions of Hungarians declared that Hungary wants to begin a new era,
[SPEAKER_16] an era of a freer, more humane, hopeful, and cooperative,
[SPEAKER_16] country proud of one another.
[SPEAKER_16] Honorable colleagues!
[SPEAKER_16] After facing the truth, but only after that, retribution is needed.
[UNKNOWN] Retribution is the mutual rebuilding of democracy.
[SPEAKER_16] This is one of its fundamental prerequisites.
[SPEAKER_16] The declaration that Hungary cannot begin a new era on the basis of concealed crimes,
[SPEAKER_16] hidden contracts, public resources put at the service of private interests,
[SPEAKER_16] and power abuses left without consequences.
[SPEAKER_16] The Hungarian people have the right to know,
[SPEAKER_16] how the power structure of the past decades functioned.
[SPEAKER_16] They have the right to know what decisions led to the situation,
[SPEAKER_16] where a significant part of the nation’s common wealth
[SPEAKER_16] became concentrated in the hands of a narrow political and economic elite.
[UNKNOWN] They have the right to know how public money became private property.
[SPEAKER_16] How state assets became political influence.
[SPEAKER_16] How public procurement became a feudal system.
[SPEAKER_16] How concessions became privileges.
[SPEAKER_16] following the formation of the new National Assembly,
[SPEAKER_16] we will submit it among the first items,
[SPEAKER_16] the law on the National Office for the Recovery and Protection of State Assets.
[UNKNOWN] that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that
[SPEAKER_16] One of the most important institutions of the 2026 system change will be.
[SPEAKER_16] Its task will be to uncover the abuses of public property in the past twenty years, to investigate corrupt and asset-stripping schemes,
[SPEAKER_16] to support criminal proceedings and to act with every legal means to recover public assets obtained unlawfully.
[SPEAKER_16] The office will not be a political tool subordinated to the government. It will operate as an autonomous, independent state body, which will only be accountable to the National Assembly.
[SPEAKER_16] Its independence, professionalism, and transparency are important because only when the institution itself is based on the rule of law can the pursuit of truth be credible.
[UNKNOWN] The office will uncover the state procurement system, concession agreements, public assets outsourced to foundations,
[SPEAKER_16] the overpricing of state investments, abuses of EU funds, financial schemes linked to the Hungarian National Bank, the financial flows of the TAO system, private equity funds, offshore-based schemes,
[SPEAKER_16] as well as any transactions where the violation of public property is suspected.
[SPEAKER_16] Suspected abuse of office, mismanagement, money laundering, budget fraud, or asset stripping.
[SPEAKER_16] Where criminal liability arises, it will be the office.
[SPEAKER_16] It will prepare and support the work of investigative and judicial bodies.
[SPEAKER_16] Where it is possible to recover assets through civil law, it will initiate claims for compensation, restitution of unjust enrichment, recovery of unjustified benefits, and asset freezes.
[SPEAKER_16] Where assets have been taken abroad, it will seek international legal assistance and cooperation.
[SPEAKER_16] Where foreign entities, concessions, or foundation-based schemes violate the public interest, it will challenge them legally.
[SPEAKER_16] I would like to state clearly: anyone who believes that political connections, party loyalty, personal loyalty, or old power protection can provide immunity from law violations,
[SPEAKER_16] abuses will be addressed.
[SPEAKER_16] Anyone who believes they can escape the consequences of actions against public property is gravely mistaken.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungary will no longer be a country without consequences.
[SPEAKER_16] What belongs to the nation must serve the nation.
[UNKNOWN] What was illegally taken away will be lawfully recovered.
[SPEAKER_16] What was concealed will be brought to light.
[SPEAKER_16] What was committed will be investigated and exposed.
[SPEAKER_16] Those responsible will be held accountable for their actions.
[SPEAKER_16] This and everything else.
[SPEAKER_16]
[SPEAKER_16] This is the essence of justice.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] And there are still some things here that we need to talk about.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Over the past years, dozens of public institutions have lost the public trust in their independence.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] They played with it, or because they never took it seriously in the first place, they emptied out the system of checks and balances.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] They left the nation to fend for itself in times of trouble.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] Therefore, I now address the holders of public office in this house of Hungarian democracy and constitutional order,
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] those in positions of dignity, those in leadership roles at institutions who have become political servants of the previous regime or always were.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Let them finally have the courage to face their own responsibility and step aside from the path of Hungary's democratic renewal.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Resign now, but at the very latest.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] By May 31st, and start salting it right away, Tamás Sulyog.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] That Tamás Sulyog, whom we heard today speaking on behalf of the entire nation, speaking about the rule of law, expressing concern for the rule of law for the first time after two years.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Irony.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] Irony, Mr. President, that in the past two years...
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] it did not succeed.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] It did not happen.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] It did not succeed, for example, when Viktor Orbán, the defeated prime minister, referred to half the country as a pest to be exterminated.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Mr. President, it did not succeed when Viktor Orbán or even the president of the Curia threatened judges or artists, persecuted them,
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] and it did not succeed either, Mr. President, when one should have stood up for the underage children ruined in the child protection system.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] And it did not succeed either when the now defeated government sent secret services against the largest opposition party.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] It did not succeed, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] And it did not succeed to speak up then,
[SPEAKER_16] when the defeated prime minister poured billions of public funds into sowing warlike hatred against every Hungarian, including our children.
[SPEAKER_16] But not even this lawyer, who is now so sensitive to the constitution and the rule of law, has ever managed to stop the anti-constitutional laws.
[SPEAKER_16] There will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there will be, there
[SPEAKER_16] meddig még lehet.
[SPEAKER_16] Tisztelt képviselők, tisztelt honfitársaim!
[UNKNOWN] Ha túl leszünk a szembenézésen és az igazságtételen, akkor megbékélésre van szükség.
[SPEAKER_16] Csak hogy nyílt, vérzősebű áldozatoktól nehéz kérni a megbékélés munkáját.
[SPEAKER_16] Márpedig az előző két évtized áldozatainak sora hosszú.
[SPEAKER_16] Meg annyi honfitársunk, akiknek az állam ma a kiszolgáltatottságot és nem a védelmet jelenti.
[SPEAKER_16] Akik segítséget kértek, de csak hallgatást kaptak.
[UNKNOWN] Akik bíztak az intézményekben, de azok cserben hagyták őket.
[SPEAKER_16] A megbocsátás nem vesz.
[SPEAKER_16] Nem felejtés.
[UNKNOWN] Valódi megbékélés nem születhet kimondatlan fájdalmakra, elhallgatott bűnökre és feldolgozatlan, elvarratlan sebekre sem.
[SPEAKER_16] Nem fogunk tudni új korszakot nyitni, ha nem vagyunk képesek szembenézni azokkal, akiket cserben hagyott, megalázott vagy magukra hagyott a magyar állam.
[UNKNOWN] Ki kell mondani, hogy ami sok honfitársunkkal történt, az elfogadhatatlan.
[SPEAKER_16] Éppen ezért engedjék meg nekem, hogy a magyar közjogi folytonosság házában Magyarország miniszterelnökeként bocsánatot kérjek.
[SPEAKER_16] Frissen megválasztott és felesküdött magyar miniszterelnökként először is bocsánatot kérjek a bicskei áldozatoknak.
[SPEAKER_16] Magyarország miniszterelnökeként bocsánatot kérek a Szöllő utcai áldozatoktól is.
[SPEAKER_16] Bocsánatot kérek a magyar gyermekvédelmi rendszer minden áldozatától.
[SPEAKER_16] From those who are still children today, and from those who have already grown up carrying within them all that was done to them, and all that the Hungarian state failed to prevent.
[SPEAKER_16] I send them this message,
[SPEAKER_16] that they are not alone.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungary will no longer turn its head away from this.
[SPEAKER_16] It is the state's duty to protect the children entrusted to it, and this duty admits of no delay, no excuses, and no political interference.
[SPEAKER_16] As Prime Minister of Hungary, I also ask for forgiveness from the victims of Bicske.
[SPEAKER_16]
[SPEAKER_16] I ask for forgiveness from all those who, over the past decades, have experienced that the state does not equally protect, and does not equally respect, its own citizens.
[SPEAKER_16] I ask for forgiveness from our fellow citizens for the lost opportunities of the previous decades.
[SPEAKER_16] For the humiliations suffered by previous ruling-party politicians.
[SPEAKER_16] For the reproduction of decline, and for the fact that too many children grew up in Hungary with fewer chances in life,
[SPEAKER_16] simply because they were born elsewhere, into a different kind of family.
[SPEAKER_16] I ask for forgiveness from those civil society members, teachers, journalists, healthcare workers,
[SPEAKER_16] and public figures who were stigmatized, harassed, or treated as enemies simply
[UNKNOWN] because they dared to raise their voices, because they stood up for the fallen,
[SPEAKER_16] because they expressed criticism, or simply held a different opinion.
[SPEAKER_16] I ask for forgiveness.
[UNKNOWN] THE TORONTO AUDIENCE
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_16] Fellow citizens!
[SPEAKER_16] The gravest sin of the past few years was that politics deliberately turned Hungarians against each other.
[SPEAKER_16] Families, friendships,
[SPEAKER_16] communities were torn apart by hatred, stigmatization, and constant incitement.
[SPEAKER_16] Millions of people were pushed into a state of fear and spiritual uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_16] Children grew up amid constant political hate campaigns.
[SPEAKER_16] The elderly feared the future.
[SPEAKER_16] The war, each other, their neighbors.
[SPEAKER_16] An entire nation’s spiritual state was poisoned by that politics which cynically toyed with the creation of artificial fear.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungary’s state can never again do this to its own citizens. Never again.
[SPEAKER_16] April 12 marked the end of this era.
[SPEAKER_16] Once and for all.
[UNKNOWN] cucumbers
[UNKNOWN] In Hungarian history, such moments are rare, when a nation so clearly and powerfully decides in favor of change.
[UNKNOWN] The Hungarian people have now given themselves a historical opportunity, and it is our duty to preserve this opportunity, to navigate it well.
[SPEAKER_16] Therefore, I would now like to ask something of every Hungarian who has voted trust in us.
[SPEAKER_16] Let us learn together from the mistakes of the past, do not leave politics to the politicians.
[UNKNOWN] Watch us, hold us accountable, demand accountability for our promises, debate with us, and never allow anyone to return with the mandate that you have given.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] And I ask that we begin together the great work of reuniting the nation.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Let us knock on each other's doors, look each other in the eye, and find out what binds us together.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Let us visit, let us see that neighbor, that friend, that family member with whom we have not been able to talk about politics for years without it causing offense,
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] or anger.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] And this time, let us not try to convince each other, not try to win another political argument, but simply try to understand one another.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Let us tell each other that even though we voted for different parties, we still love this beautiful country just the same, we still want safety for our children,
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] just the same peaceful, functioning, fair country.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] We want to live in a humane, humanly just country.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Let us relearn the simplest rules of living together in a shared nation.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] That it is indeed possible to argue with one another without wanting to wipe the other off the face of the earth, to expel them from the entire nation, from its body.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] That it is possible to think as members of a common homeland despite political differences.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] That it is possible to love Hungary equally, even while thinking completely differently about the world and politics.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Therefore, national reconciliation does not depend on a single law, a single speech, or a single electoral victory.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] It depends on whether the Hungarian people will once again be able to turn to one another with trust.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Whether we will be able to once again assume good intentions in one another.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Whether we will be able to once again listen to each other without immediately seeing a traitor or an enemy in the other.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Whether we will be able to once again view Hungary as a shared story.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] I believe, I believe we will be able to.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] In fact, the Hungarian nation is waiting for the beginning of this shared story as one people.
[UNKNOWN] cucumbers
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_16] Honfitársaim! The soon-to-be-formed Tisza government will be the government of every Hungarian.
[SPEAKER_16] Our goal is that every Hungarian person becomes a true citizen of this country.
[SPEAKER_16] Not just the wealthy, not just the influential, not just the politically loyal, but everyone who lives in this country, works, raises children, pays taxes, hopes, and wants a future for themselves.
[SPEAKER_16] Because the homeland is not a privilege. The homeland is a shared home.
[SPEAKER_16] And the Hungarian state must finally turn toward every person.
[SPEAKER_16] With the same respect, the same dignity, and the same responsibility.
[SPEAKER_16] Honored fellow citizens!
[UNKNOWN] For me, a free Hungary means what Adi Endre expressed so well: every person is royalty.
[SPEAKER_16] It means that in this country, every person matters.
[SPEAKER_16] Every Hungarian has the right to feel that the Hungarian state works for them, protects them, and respects their dignity.
[SPEAKER_16] Citizen, the little boy from Sükösd, who may be visiting Budapest for the first time, and certainly for the first time in the most beautiful building in the world.
[SPEAKER_16] And who looks at this country with the same curiosity as any child in a big city.
[SPEAKER_16] We will work for him too, because he deserves the best school, the best teacher, and the same opportunity for success.
[SPEAKER_16] Citizen, Martin, who ran away from the foster home, whom the state left alone too often.
[UNKNOWN] Citizen, someone who needs to be protected.
[SPEAKER_16] We will work for him too, because he has the right to live in safety, in love, and with dignity, to grow.
[UNKNOWN] Citizen, Martin, who ran away from the foster home, whom the state left alone too often.
[SPEAKER_16] And the four-children mother, who counts every month how much money she still has left from her salary,
[SPEAKER_16] while at the same time working, raising children, hoping, and trying to find her place.
[SPEAKER_16] We will work for her as well, because her work keeps this country alive just as much as anyone else's, for example here.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_16] A citizen is also that elderly man who, after forty years of honest work, wants nothing else but peace, security, and a little respect at the end of his life.
[SPEAKER_16] And a citizen is also that retired woman who only longs for not having to choose between healer and cure anymore.
[SPEAKER_16] Between instruments, food, or heating. We will work for her as well.
[SPEAKER_16] A citizen is also that farmer in the countryside who has been cultivating the same land for generations.
[SPEAKER_16] And a citizen is the young entrepreneur who believes that with honest work,
[SPEAKER_16] it is also possible to build a future in Hungary.
[SPEAKER_16] We will work for him as well.
[SPEAKER_16] A citizen is the teacher who still believes in the vocation of education despite all the difficulties.
[SPEAKER_16] A citizen is the caregiver who works night after night for people's lives.
[SPEAKER_16] A citizen is the police officer, the firefighter, the paramedic, the social worker.
[SPEAKER_16] Who serves the country even when he often does not receive the proper respect himself.
[SPEAKER_16] We will work for them as well, for all of them.
[SPEAKER_16] A citizen is also the Hungarian living abroad who belongs to this nation just as much.
[SPEAKER_16] A citizen is the police officer who, despite all the difficulties, still works night after night for people's lives.
[SPEAKER_16] We will work for them as well, for all of them.
[SPEAKER_16] A citizen is also the young person who had to leave the country, but who, with every call home, thinks of Hungary with pain and love.
[UNKNOWN] A citizen is the police officer who, with every call home, thinks of Hungary with pain and love.
[SPEAKER_16] We will work for them as well, for all of them.
[SPEAKER_16] No one shall suffer disadvantage because of their origin, their love, or their political opinion.
[SPEAKER_16] We will work for every Hungarian person.
[UNKNOWN] We will work for every Hungarian person.
[UNKNOWN] Because dear colleagues, if it is not possible to go home, it is not possible to go home.
[SPEAKER_16] Because dear colleagues, if it is not possible to go home, it is not possible to go home.
[SPEAKER_16] And there will be no fewer privileges.
[SPEAKER_16] Our wonderful homeland is the common home of every Hungarian person.
[UNKNOWN] Esteemed fellow citizens, a fresh start is needed.
[SPEAKER_16] Step by step, brick by brick, we will rebuild what the past decades have torn down.
[SPEAKER_16] The state, trust, public services, respect, and the various lives.
[SPEAKER_16]
[SPEAKER_16] The fair competition, national unity, and hope.
[SPEAKER_16] We will build a Hungary where our fellow citizens living in poverty
[SPEAKER_16] once again have the chance to rise up.
[SPEAKER_16] Where the fate of a single child is not sealed by where they are born,
[SPEAKER_16] what kind of family they come from, or which town in the country they grow up in.
[SPEAKER_16] We will build a country where the elderly are respected citizens in their final years, where the pension once again provides security,
[SPEAKER_16] and where no one, after a lifetime of work, has to choose between heating and food.
[SPEAKER_16] és ahol egy életmunkája után senkinek sem kell választani a fűtés vagy az élelmiszer között.
[SPEAKER_16] We will build a Hungary where the healthcare system provides timely assistance,
[SPEAKER_16] where people's fate is decided by professionals,
[SPEAKER_16] preferably qualified professionals, functioning hospitals, accessible family doctors,
[SPEAKER_16] respected nurses and doctors. We will build a Hungary
[SPEAKER_16] where daycare, kindergarten, and school once again become the gates to upward mobility,
[SPEAKER_16] where nannies,
[SPEAKER_16] kindergarten teachers, and school teachers are respected individuals and children are not statistics,
[UNKNOWN] where knowledge is not a privilege and where even a talented young person born into a poor family
[SPEAKER_16] will also find the path open toward success.
[SPEAKER_16] We will build a Hungary where child protection truly means protection.
[SPEAKER_16] We will uncover the child abuse cases of the past years,
[SPEAKER_16] strengthen child protection, and make children's safety clear,
[SPEAKER_16] the protection of children, child abuse, child abuse,
[SPEAKER_16] is one of the most important duties of the Hungarian state.
[SPEAKER_16] We will build a Hungary that once again welcomes Hungarians living abroad,
[SPEAKER_16] where once again hundreds of thousands will feel it is worth returning home,
[SPEAKER_16] because one can also live safely, have children, build a home,
[SPEAKER_16] plan for the future here, and where their compatriots who have moved abroad remain part of the life of the Hungarian nation, the life of the Hungarian nation, the life of the Hungarian nation,
[SPEAKER_16] and the country counts on them as part of its shared future.
[SPEAKER_16] részei maradnak, akikre az ország a közös jövőinek részeként számít.
[SPEAKER_16] We will build a country where work once again ensures a decent standard of living,
[SPEAKER_16] where wages gradually catch up to European levels,
[SPEAKER_16] the tax system becomes fairer and more predictable,
[SPEAKER_16] the energy of businesses is directed toward development, innovation and
[SPEAKER_16] job creation, and where the growth of the Hungarian economy finally benefits Hungarian families as well.
[SPEAKER_16] In the past years, hundreds of billions were spent supporting foreign investments
[SPEAKER_16] that treated Hungary as a simple assembly and investment zone.
[SPEAKER_16] Profit became more important than people, the natural environment, and the safety of local communities.
[SPEAKER_16] And it was the most grateful Hungarian government that allowed this, indeed, supported it, and still supports it.
[UNKNOWN] There were companies that behaved in Hungary
[SPEAKER_16] as if the same rules that apply to Hungarian citizens and companies did not apply to them.
[SPEAKER_16] And they were able to do this because the most grateful Hungarian government allowed it, indeed, supported it, and was proud of it.
[SPEAKER_16] We will put an end to this.
[SPEAKER_16] We will build a Hungary where the investor is everything.
[SPEAKER_16] Investors respect our laws, our environment,
[SPEAKER_16] our employees, and the safety of our local communities.
[UNKNOWN] We will build a Hungary where public funds are once again public funds,
[SPEAKER_16] where public property is once again national wealth.
[SPEAKER_16] And where no one can ever again think that they can obtain what belongs to every Hungarian through political connections,
[SPEAKER_16] party loyalty, or personal loyalty.
[SPEAKER_16] We will build a Hungary that once again has dignity in Europe and in the world,
[SPEAKER_16] that does not drift out of the federal systems it has chosen itself, and does not grovel.
[SPEAKER_16] It does not grovel before foreign interests, and does not confuse sovereignty with isolation.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungary's place is in Europe, and we are building a strong, respected, European Hungary that clearly represents its own interests.
[UNKNOWN] We will be the government of national self-determination, restoring Hungary's international credibility,
[SPEAKER_16] rebuilding our federal relationships, and bringing back the EU funds that belong to the Hungarian people and Hungarian businesses.
[SPEAKER_16] We must say it out loud...
[SPEAKER_16] We declare that the country of Saint Stephen is not a pass-through house.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungary has been the homeland of the Hungarians in the Carpathian Basin for 1100 years.
[UNKNOWN] We are open to every person who comes to us with peace, respect, and a spirit of cooperation.
[SPEAKER_16] But those who want to exploit this country, who want to establish influence, subjugation, or dependency in Hungary,
[SPEAKER_16] we will deal with them most decisively. We will act most decisively against them.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungary will once again truly be a sovereign country, and it will remain so.
[SPEAKER_16] This will be the functional Hungary, and this will be the humane Hungary.
[SPEAKER_16] Functional, because the state will finally do its job.
[UNKNOWN] It heals, it teaches, it carries out its duties.
[SPEAKER_16]
[SPEAKER_16] It protects, organizes transportation, provides security, creates opportunities, and accounts accurately for the assets entrusted to it.
[UNKNOWN] It is humane because it does not forget that behind every decision there are human fates.
[SPEAKER_16] Children, parents, the elderly, the sick, workers, teachers, caregivers,
[SPEAKER_16] law enforcement officers, social workers, entrepreneurs, farmers, students,
[SPEAKER_16] Hungarians living in the country and abroad.
[SPEAKER_16] Honorable colleagues!
[SPEAKER_16] I ask you, whether you sit in the governing party or the opposition faction,
[SPEAKER_16] to understand the message of the election that stands behind us,
[UNKNOWN] and its historical weight.
[UNKNOWN] The governing party faction, which now holds a two-thirds majority, has a particularly great responsibility.
[SPEAKER_16] In Hungarian history, it has happened too often that a political community
[UNKNOWN] confused electoral victory with moral and political infallibility.
[SPEAKER_16] We must not commit this mistake.
[SPEAKER_16] Therefore, we regard even our own power as limited.
[SPEAKER_16] We will initiate a comprehensive review of Hungary's constitutional system,
[SPEAKER_16] in order to ensure that power does not concentrate to such an extent in this country again.
[UNKNOWN] We will strengthen the system of checks and balances.
[SPEAKER_16] We will restore the institutions.
[SPEAKER_16] The true independence of institutions.
[SPEAKER_16] And we will initiate the limitation of the number of prime ministerial terms.
[SPEAKER_16] Because in a democratic country
[SPEAKER_16] power must always be within limits.
[SPEAKER_16] Freedom is not enough to be won.
[SPEAKER_16] It must also be protected from the current power.
[SPEAKER_16] And I especially address my fellow parliamentarians,
[SPEAKER_16] to enter this house every day
[SPEAKER_16] so that their own selves from one and a half to two years ago would be proud of them.
[UNKNOWN] Remember that person,
[SPEAKER_16] who recently stood behind a counter in a square,
[SPEAKER_16] often uncertainly, often fearfully,
[UNKNOWN] but still resolutely, because there was still one last chance left
[SPEAKER_16] for this beautiful country.
[UNKNOWN] Remember how you felt then,
[SPEAKER_16] when the Hungarian public life seemed hopeless.
[SPEAKER_16] When you thought that perhaps after 2026, you might not even have a future in this beautiful country.
[SPEAKER_16] Let this memory be present in every decision you make.
[SPEAKER_16] Surround yourselves with people
[SPEAKER_16] who remind you of this every single day.
[SPEAKER_16] Because the first temptation of power is always
[SPEAKER_16] to make us forget where we came from and where we set out to go.
[SPEAKER_16] And we have asked for and accepted all of this.
[SPEAKER_16] But our opposition colleagues also bear a great responsibility,
[SPEAKER_16] one they must face.
[SPEAKER_16] Therefore, let me now address the former ruling party members,
[SPEAKER_16] the Fidesz representatives present here.
[SPEAKER_16] We naturally accept the legal outcome of the elections,
[SPEAKER_16] and we begin parliamentary work with mutual respect.
[SPEAKER_16] However, there is one issue we cannot pass by in silence.
[SPEAKER_16] Ág Péter.
[SPEAKER_16] The circumstances surrounding Ág Péter’s mandate point to a single electoral district.
[SPEAKER_16] A political maneuver appeared there,
[SPEAKER_16] which is unworthy of Hungarian democracy,
[SPEAKER_16] and which must and will be permanently removed from public life.
[SPEAKER_16] The citizens of Northern Vas County have no reason to fear.
[SPEAKER_16] They cannot be subjected to any political retaliation or disadvantage.
[SPEAKER_16] Their interests will indeed be represented in this house.
[SPEAKER_16] Their interests will continue to be represented,
[SPEAKER_16] even if we clearly state our commitment to the defense of Hungarian democracy and the rule of law,
[SPEAKER_16] against manipulative, petty, and illegal election methods.
[SPEAKER_16] hogy manipulatív, piti, jogellenes választási módszerekre
[SPEAKER_16] It is impossible to build a rule of law and democracy on such foundations.
[SPEAKER_16] It is particularly serious that in this campaign, right here
[UNKNOWN] an almost Hungarian democratic figure,
[SPEAKER_16] has managed to cast doubt on his Hungarian identity,
[SPEAKER_16] despite—or precisely because of—his birth in Upper Hungary
[SPEAKER_16] he is a member of the same Hungarian nation,
[SPEAKER_16] just like any of us in this room, dear Lázár János.
[SPEAKER_16] Stromba Victoria!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you very much!
[SPEAKER_16] If the representative thinks so, I am happy to give her the floor,
[SPEAKER_04] or to the chairperson for an apology.
[SPEAKER_16] Stromba Victoria’s story warns us
[SPEAKER_16] where it leads when politics repeatedly seeks to determine
[SPEAKER_16] who belongs to the nation and who does not.
[SPEAKER_16] We will put an end to this era, in fact it has already ended,
[SPEAKER_16] on April 12th.
[SPEAKER_16] Honorable Fidesz representatives!
[SPEAKER_16] You now represent the marginalized, disappointed,
[SPEAKER_16] often uncertain citizens in this house.
[SPEAKER_16] jelentik ebben a házban.
[SPEAKER_16] We respect this.
[SPEAKER_16] The election result gave us a clear mandate to govern,
[SPEAKER_16] but this does not make any less important the millions of Hungarians
[SPEAKER_16] who believed in a different political community, made a different decision,
[SPEAKER_16] and envisioned a different future for Hungary.
[SPEAKER_16] Naturally, you primarily represent them, and we also represent them,
[SPEAKER_16] but this also makes your responsibility historic.
[SPEAKER_16] The reunification of the nation also requires you.
[SPEAKER_16] In order for Hungary to start with a clean slate, it is in our common interest, over the past 20 years,
[SPEAKER_16] to uncover the sins of the past 20 years, to reveal the agent files.
[SPEAKER_16] It is in our common interest to uncover the fate of public assets,
[UNKNOWN] and the establishment of a national property recovery and protection authority,
[SPEAKER_16] and the setting up of the office as well.
[SPEAKER_16] This is not the concern of a single political side.
[SPEAKER_16] These are the prerequisites for every Hungarian finally to see
[SPEAKER_16] what decisions were made, who made them, who carried them out,
[SPEAKER_16] who benefited from them, and who is burdened with what responsibility.
[SPEAKER_16] It will have great significance and historical weight that you, the opposition,
[SPEAKER_16] will take a stand, and how you vote on these issues.
[SPEAKER_16] Agent files, uncovering the fate of public assets, national property recovery and protection authority.
[SPEAKER_16] No, my AVH is already in the past, Mr. Representative.
[SPEAKER_16] That is why I ask you, that is why I ask you, dear Fidesz colleagues in the National Assembly,
[SPEAKER_16] be our opponents if you deem it appropriate, be our strict critics,
[SPEAKER_16] if we make mistakes, but also be our partners in making Hungary finally a clean, transparent
[SPEAKER_16] and a common country for all Hungarians.
[SPEAKER_16] Those who are sitting in the opposition today can also have a historical role.
[SPEAKER_16] No less than to show their own voters that from defeat, not further, not additional hatred,
[SPEAKER_16] but a responsible, constitutional, patriotic opposition can also be born.
[SPEAKER_16] Distinguished compatriots, Hungarians!
[SPEAKER_16] In 1990, on the first day of the inaugural session of the newly elected National Assembly at the birth of modern Hungarian democracy,
[SPEAKER_16] an 88-year-old American stood before the inaugural session of the National Assembly,
[SPEAKER_16] an elderly emigrant walked up to this pulpit to speak to the representatives.
[SPEAKER_16] His name was Béla Varga.
[SPEAKER_16] He was the former president of the 1946, the last freely elected National Assembly before communism.
[SPEAKER_16] His words, Béla Varga’s words, are just as relevant today as they were back then.
[SPEAKER_16] Human freedom is not a circumstance, but a task.
[SPEAKER_16] With the falling of the chains comes the human duty we impose on ourselves.
[SPEAKER_16] It is sometimes harder to be free than to be a prisoner.
[SPEAKER_16] I stand before you at a historical moment,
[SPEAKER_16] and Hungary also stands before a historical moment.
[SPEAKER_16] On April 12, the Hungarian people decided to take their fate into their own hands.
[SPEAKER_16] They decided to teach the world that freedom is not a noun, but a verb.
[SPEAKER_16] An invincible, creative, uplifting action, nothing can stand in its way.
[SPEAKER_16] Therefore, every Hungarian deserves gratitude.
[SPEAKER_16] But as Béla Varga warned us, freedom in itself is no guarantee of anything.
[UNKNOWN] In fact, freedom is a serious responsibility.
[SPEAKER_16] Responsibility for our country.
[SPEAKER_16] Responsibility for one another.
[SPEAKER_16] Responsibility for what kind of country we leave for our children.
[SPEAKER_16] It is up to us how we live with the freedom we have now received as a gift from the Hungarian nation.
[SPEAKER_16] We must now transform freedom into work.
[SPEAKER_16] Hope into functioning, working institutions.
[SPEAKER_16] Trust into laws.
[SPEAKER_16] Authorization into service.
[SPEAKER_16] And victory into better, more humane everyday life.
[SPEAKER_16] If we do this, then in a few years we will not only be able to say that we have ended this era,
[SPEAKER_16] but also that we have built a country in which, at last, everyone can live well, do good things,
[SPEAKER_16] raise children, and be a good Hungarian.
[SPEAKER_16] We will work for this every single day with humility, service, and teamwork.
[UNKNOWN] Fellow countrymen, God bless Hungary!
[SPEAKER_16] May God bless every Hungarian at home and around the world!
[SPEAKER_16] Thank you for listening!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you for listening!
[SPEAKER_13] Mr. Prime Minister, thank you for sharing your thoughts!
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable Members of Parliament, dear fellow citizens!
[SPEAKER_13] Uniquely in the history of the National Assembly's opening sessions, a heartwarming performance is now to follow.
[SPEAKER_13] We believe that today is not only the day of the members of parliament, but of the entire country.
[SPEAKER_13] During the past two years, Mr. Prime Minister has traveled the countryside, where he met with many talented young people.
[SPEAKER_13] This is how he came to know the Sükösdi Súgó Tambora band.
[SPEAKER_13] We will hear their performance of "Green is the forest, green is the mountain,"
[SPEAKER_13] as well as the songs beginning with "Spring wind stirs the water," led by Nébül Zsolt.
[SPEAKER_13] Please welcome them warmly!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you very much!
[UNKNOWN] S cucumbers that that that
[UNKNOWN] Fortune comes and goes, with sword and scale, the weight is over, comfort, expertise, it can be the world, and you can reach the world's enemies.
[UNKNOWN] My troubles are silent, comfort, fact, I don't work, only with indicators, Jesus' essence, may it break for us.
[UNKNOWN] May God have mercy on me, through heaven we go further for us, they divide and recognize me, forever the grapes we have made.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[UNKNOWN] The Community of Title Songs
[UNKNOWN]
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13] Dear young people, in the past few minutes, you stood in the heart of the country, where your talent and perseverance brought you.
[SPEAKER_13] We work so that this will be what truly matters. Thank you for your uplifting performance.
[SPEAKER_13] Honorable members of parliament, dear compatriots, please stand up and let us sing together the national anthem, the song of joy, and the Székelyhímúz.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13] Thank you.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13] [SPEAKER_13] before the lesson.
[SPEAKER_05] [SPEAKER_05] Color guards,
[SPEAKER_05] [SPEAKER_05] right, left!
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] Att!
[SPEAKER_05] [SPEAKER_05] Step!
[SPEAKER_05] [SPEAKER_05] In!
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] Tui!
[SPEAKER_13] [SPEAKER_13] Dear attendees! I close the founding session.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you!
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] Oh, Ladies and Gentlemen! I am glad you are still here, I am glad you are still here.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] The truth is that this was really touching,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] and I very much thank you for being here.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] It was very nice to see all of this.
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] The words spoken in the past moments were hard, straightforward, and uplifting,
[SPEAKER_11] [SPEAKER_11] and it was truly uplifting to witness everything that took place within these parliamentary walls.
[SPEAKER_11] I don't know how others felt about it, but as we watched it here,
[SPEAKER_11] we were deeply moved by the performance of the Sükösd Danubia Tambora Band.
[SPEAKER_11] The truth is, it was truly inspiring to see all of this,
[SPEAKER_11] that back during the country tour, Péter met these young people,
[SPEAKER_11] and they played for him.
[SPEAKER_11] I remember, this video went viral, it spread all over the internet.
[SPEAKER_11] Everyone was watching it, everyone was sharing it online.
[SPEAKER_11] And now, to put it mildly, we've been quite overwhelmed by these human stories in the past few minutes,
[SPEAKER_11] in the recent period we witnessed within these parliamentary walls.
[SPEAKER_11] So it was genuinely good and exciting to see,
[SPEAKER_11] and it was good to see these songs performed by the Sükösd Danubia Tambora Band.
[SPEAKER_11] This will likely be a lifelong experience for these young people.
[SPEAKER_11] And how wonderful, by the way, the Hungarian language is, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_11] So, how many beautiful and uplifting phrases we have heard,
[SPEAKER_11] wrapped in many beautiful, flowery words,
[SPEAKER_11] and in reality, we have just three words that, when put together, say it all.
[SPEAKER_11] This was good.
[SPEAKER_11] So I think many of us would agree with that,
[SPEAKER_11] but the ceremony is starting, and the remaining part of the program is beginning,
[SPEAKER_11] which takes place inside the house.
[SPEAKER_11] At the moment, first the guests and the two opposition factions,
[SPEAKER_11] namely Fidesz and Our Homeland, are leaving the chamber,
[SPEAKER_11] and the representatives of the Tisza faction are just exiting the building to pay their respects,
[SPEAKER_11] while the military honors are also beginning,
[UNKNOWN] and the members of the 32nd Guard Regiment of the Hungarian Defence Forces are marching onto the square,
[UNKNOWN] the members of the 32nd Guard Regiment of the Hungarian Defence Forces,
[SPEAKER_11] but the Hussar Squadron of Count Nádasdi Ferenc will also be present with us,
[SPEAKER_11] and the National Lobas Honor Unit is arriving,
[SPEAKER_11] as well as the Central Band of the Hungarian Defence Forces will provide the music.
[SPEAKER_11] This is Hungary's largest representative military band,
[SPEAKER_11] whose primary task is to provide musical support for the highest level of state and military protocol and events,
[SPEAKER_11] as well as for major social events.
[SPEAKER_11] For over 100 years, the Central Band has represented the spiritual and cultural values of the Hungarian defence forces,
[SPEAKER_11] as well as the country's national traditions.
[SPEAKER_11] The history of the Central Band actually began with the formation of the band of the first professional infantry regiment of the Hungarian Army, its predecessor.
[SPEAKER_11] We have to go all the way back to 1896 for this,
[SPEAKER_11] when the country's first professional military band was established,
[SPEAKER_11] right here in Budapest.
[SPEAKER_11] Under the professional leadership of renowned military conductors, the band became a celebrated ensemble known throughout the country and in Europe.
[SPEAKER_11] Naturally, the national cavalry honor unit will also be present.
[SPEAKER_11] The motto on the standard symbolizes the members of the honor unit's faith and dedication to homeland and honor.
[SPEAKER_11] The Hungarian Central Military Bands were established by decree effective January 1, 2001.
[SPEAKER_11] The task of the honor unit is to emphasize our state and national holidays,
[SPEAKER_11] by performing ceremonial mounted escort duties on distinguished occasions, utilizing the values of Hungarian hussar tradition.
[SPEAKER_11] The hussar uniform of the honor unit, in tribute to the 1848 honor of the 8th Coburg Hussar Regiment,
[SPEAKER_11] is historically accurate and authentic according to the officer's regulations.
[SPEAKER_11] In recognition of the activities of the honor unit, Ferenc Mádl, President of the Hungarian Republic,
[SPEAKER_11] presented a unit flag to the National Equestrian Honor Unit of the Hungarian Republic on August 20, 2001.
[UNKNOWN] And with us here on the grounds is also the Nádasdi Ferenc hussar company.
[SPEAKER_11] The Kincsem National Equestrian Program, adopted in 2012, stipulated that
[SPEAKER_11] the cavalry capability, which had ceased in the mid-1950s, must be reinstated in the Hungarian Defence Forces as the hussar unit.
[SPEAKER_11] As a result of this, on July 1, 2020, in Szilvásvárad, the newly established Hussar Subunit Preparatory Staff was formed,
[SPEAKER_11] from which the Gróf Mádasdi Ferenc hussar company was later developed, effective from February 1, 2023.
[SPEAKER_11] The subunit operating under the name of the hussar company.
[SPEAKER_11] Hungary has given a unit type, the hussar unit type, to 34 countries around the world, which has been recognized as a Hungarian national treasure since 2017,
[SPEAKER_11] and until now, had no representative in Hungary itself.
[SPEAKER_11] Strangely enough, by reviving the hussar company, the first regular unit established in 1688 has once again been reinstated in the Hungarian armed forces.
[SPEAKER_11] The tasks stemming from the fundamental purpose of the hussar company include ensuring equestrian ceremonial duties at state and military events,
[SPEAKER_11] conducting demonstrations, performing military operational tasks, and participating in domestic and international horse competitions as well.
[SPEAKER_11] In the meantime, the members of the Tisza faction are already coming out of the building and will line up here on the main steps of the parliament.
[SPEAKER_11] A group photo will follow here, and Peter Magyar will also give a speech in the remaining time this afternoon.
[SPEAKER_11] We will also provide a musical program; a musical performance is coming and will take place in the following time.
[SPEAKER_11] Let me also say a few more words about the 32nd Testőr Regiment of the Hungarian Defence Forces.
[SPEAKER_11] It is one of the prominent military units of the Hungarian Army, primarily performing state, ceremonial, honor guard,
[SPEAKER_11] and facility protection tasks.
[SPEAKER_11] The regiment operates under the command of the Vitéz Szurmai Sándor Budapest Garrison Brigade of the Hungarian Defence Forces.
[SPEAKER_11] The soldiers of the testőr regiment simultaneously perform military and representational duties in their daily service.
[SPEAKER_11] In their ceremonial uniforms, they represent Hungarian military traditions, while the young military representatives receive modern training,
[SPEAKER_11] and they also possess various skills.
[SPEAKER_11] Therefore, the activities of the unit play a significant role in ensuring that the Hungarian Defence Forces present a unified, professional image before the domestic and international public.
[SPEAKER_11] The commander of the honor unit is Colonel Tamás Zsolnai, the commander of the 32nd Testőr Regiment.
[SPEAKER_11] The commander of the flag escort is Major Rihárd Haszlinger, the chief of staff of the military organization.
[SPEAKER_11] They will be the main participants of the military honors in the following time.
[SPEAKER_11] We are looking forward to a very impressive, very beautiful and dignified event in the coming time.
[SPEAKER_11] I hope everyone is feeling very well. How are you all at Kossuth Square?
[SPEAKER_11] We are glad that so many of us are here, and we are glad that so many of you have come here.
[SPEAKER_11] We can say that the venue is full.
[SPEAKER_11] We can also say that a great number of people are following the broadcast online.
[SPEAKER_11] Perhaps never in the history of Hungary have so many people followed the opening session.
[SPEAKER_11] So many and such a large number.
[SPEAKER_11] So, if someone happens to be online and wants to share this experience with their friends and acquaintances,
[SPEAKER_11] feel free to share the links to this broadcast.
[SPEAKER_11] On YouTube, Facebook, as it is commonly said.
[SPEAKER_11] And this way, the experience of this beautiful day, the memory of this beautiful day, will also reach more people.
[SPEAKER_11] The more people, the better.
[SPEAKER_11] We will still have very important tasks this afternoon,
[SPEAKER_11] because after the representatives from Tisza arrive here at Kossuth Square,
[SPEAKER_11] young Balázs Elemér will play the piano.
[SPEAKER_11] After that, Magyar Péter will also arrive with his children.
[SPEAKER_11] After that, we will listen together to the song "You Are Beautiful, You Are Magnificent, Hungary."
[SPEAKER_11] And then the event will continue with the ceremonial raising of the flag of Hungary,
[SPEAKER_11] the ceremony.
[SPEAKER_11] After this, the ceremony will continue with the song "Magyarország" by Olá Ibolya.
[SPEAKER_11] A choir will perform this song.
[SPEAKER_11] Hopefully, Olá Ibolya will also meet Magyar Péter on the stairs.
[SPEAKER_11] And this opportunity, I think, will be available to everyone at the end of the event,
[SPEAKER_11] because, as Magyar Péter put it, after the official program ends here,
[SPEAKER_11] let there be dancing.
[SPEAKER_11] And this opportunity, I think, will be available to everyone at the end of the event,
[SPEAKER_11] and to this, a DJ will provide the music for the rest of the day.
[SPEAKER_11] So, I think we will say goodbye to this Saturday with a very beautiful sunset and a very beautiful day.
[UNKNOWN] Here on the square, Péter Magyar addresses those present on-site as well.
[SPEAKER_11] After his recent remarks, he still has something more to say, and he will deliver these live for us right here on Kossuth Square.
[SPEAKER_11] After that, we will listen to the song "Mi vagyunk a Grund" performed by József Wunderlich, Zsombor Ertl, Dino Benjamin, László Józan, Péter Rejder, Balázs Szántó, András Tóth, and Péter Virág.
[SPEAKER_11] After that, Karamell will arrive and bring us the recording titled "Szálok a dallal."
[SPEAKER_11] After that, a surprise performance, a surprise song, and a surprise performer will follow.
[SPEAKER_11] I was sworn to secrecy, so I cannot reveal it, and I don't know how long this will go on.
[SPEAKER_11] It might actually be revealed on stage.
[SPEAKER_11] Everyone will find out soon enough.
[SPEAKER_11] But a popular performer, one we all greatly love and cherish, is coming to us, and we will listen to one of his iconic recordings.
[SPEAKER_11] And I think we all know this one by heart, and we will be able to sing it together with him.
[SPEAKER_11] So, he is arriving, and of course, in this song, he will not be alone as the songwriter and performer, but he will have helpers, namely Szebényi.
[SPEAKER_11]
[SPEAKER_11] Daniel, Sándor Födő, Áron Somodi, Bence Szabolcsi, József Wunderlich, and Marci Mieringer are arriving.
[SPEAKER_11] So, they will also perform a recording, a song, and in the meantime, as you can see on the screen, the Tiszai representatives are arriving, with Péter Magyar, the freshly elected Prime Minister, leading the way.
[UNKNOWN] And if I see correctly, Péter Magyar is arriving once again under the leadership of Tamás Tóth, just as...
[SPEAKER_11] ...he has always done during the country tours of the past two years.
[SPEAKER_11] So, the floor now belongs to the parliament.
[UNKNOWN] I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the cucumbers I want to go to the
[UNKNOWN] A TORONTOS KÖZÖN
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_06] A TORONTOS KÖZÖN
[SPEAKER_06]
[UNKNOWN] A TORONTOS KÖZÖN
[SPEAKER_06] A TORONTOS KÖZÖN
[SPEAKER_00] A TORONTOS KÖZÖN
[SPEAKER_11] A TORONTOS KÖZÖN
[SPEAKER_06] A TORONTOS KÖZÖN
[SPEAKER_12] Good day to you!
[SPEAKER_12] Honorable Ladies and Gentlemen!
[SPEAKER_12] With great affection, I welcome everyone present,
[SPEAKER_12] as well as those following today's event online.
[SPEAKER_12] I am Solti Lille, and it is a tremendous honor for me,
[SPEAKER_12] to be one of the hosts of this wonderful event.
[SPEAKER_12] I am pleased to announce that today,
[SPEAKER_12] on May 9, 2026, the New Hungarian National Assembly was established.
[SPEAKER_12] The Prime Minister of Hungary is now Magyar Péter!
[SPEAKER_12] I kindly ask you to warmly welcome the members of the Tisza faction,
[SPEAKER_12] who are now leaving the building of the parliament and joining us here at Kossuth Square.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you!
[SPEAKER_12] Young Balázs Elemér will accompany on the piano.
[SPEAKER_12] Following this, Mr. Magyar Péter, the Prime Minister, will arrive with his children.
[SPEAKER_12] During this time, the song "Szép vagy, Gyönyörű vagy, Magyarország" will be played.
[SPEAKER_12] The song will be performed by Hajnalka Héty, Bence Fleischer, young Balázs Elemér, Máté Takács, and Adrién Szekeres.
[SPEAKER_12] Please welcome them with great love!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you!
[UNKNOWN] cucumbers
[UNKNOWN] Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_06] Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_06] the wildflower of my homeland's meadow.
[SPEAKER_06] the violin calls me,
[SPEAKER_06] a beautiful, lovely country waits.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] The cucumbers will be clean.
[UNKNOWN] [SPEAKER_10] Greetings will be on the cucumbers.
[SPEAKER_10] [SPEAKER_10] Greetings will be on the cucumbers.
[SPEAKER_10]
[UNKNOWN] [SPEAKER_10] Greetings will be on the cucumbers.
[SPEAKER_10] [SPEAKER_10] Greetings will be on the cucumbers.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] How!
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_10] [UNKNOWN] How!
[SPEAKER_10] The commander of the ceremonial unit reports,
[SPEAKER_10] on the occasion of the National Assembly's convening,
[SPEAKER_10] for the ceremonial raising of the flag of Hungary,
[UNKNOWN] the 32nd Guard Regiment, the Count Nádasdi Ferenc Hussar Squadron
[SPEAKER_10] and the National Cavalry Ceremonial Unit have formed up.
[UNKNOWN] cucumbers that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that
[UNKNOWN] with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish Community, with the Turkish
[UNKNOWN] Turkish
[SPEAKER_10] Attention, arms down, arms up, forward!
[UNKNOWN] Attention, salute, to the right, the flag of Hungary, salute, stand down!
[UNKNOWN] Attention, salute, to the right, the flag escort of Hungary, follow me, march, go!
[SPEAKER_10] Attention, arms down, arms up, forward!
[SPEAKER_17] Attention, salute, to the right, the flag escort of Hungary, follow me, march, go!
[UNKNOWN] Attention, salute, to the right, the flag escort of Hungary, follow me, march, go!
[SPEAKER_03] Honor, reception, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity, activity,
[UNKNOWN] Köszönöm, hogy megnéztétek!
[SPEAKER_10] Tisztetség! Fogadás balról Magyarország zászlajának! Tiszte!
[UNKNOWN] Tisztetség! Fogadás balról Magyarország zászlajának! Tiszte!
[SPEAKER_17] Tisztetség! Fogadás balról Magyarország zászlajának! Tiszte!
[SPEAKER_10] Tisztesség!
[UNKNOWN] Tegyvert!
[UNKNOWN] Vall!
[SPEAKER_10] Ró!
[UNKNOWN] Tisztesség!
[SPEAKER_10] Good!
[UNKNOWN] Well!
[SPEAKER_10] Tisztesség!
[UNKNOWN] Honesty!
[SPEAKER_10] After her, go!
[UNKNOWN] [SPEAKER_05] Step!
[SPEAKER_10] Go!
[SPEAKER_06] Tisztesség!
[UNKNOWN] Tisztesség!
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_06] Tisztesség!
[UNKNOWN] Tisztesség!
[UNKNOWN] With the Turkish Community
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_06] With the Turkish Community
[UNKNOWN] With the Turkish Community
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] The Hungarian sick minister first, again!
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] HONOR! HONOR! HONOR!
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] There is a country where I walked in my dreams,
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Hungary, where I saw my own face in the crowd.
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] There is abundance in the embrace, faithfulness in the true cause.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] You were abundance, I already guard this face.
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Hungary, I believe in my dream for the rest of my life.
[UNKNOWN] [SPEAKER_07] Hungary!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Hungary!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] You are written in my heart.
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] You are entrusted to my soul.
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Hungary!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Now, you lead me, and for what I must do, help me!
[SPEAKER_07] Be the certainty that lies in tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_07] I give only my life.
[UNKNOWN] May I go as one who is loved.
[SPEAKER_07] May I go as one who is loved.
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_07] Come and once again, when a new day comes at night, come to me!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Come and embrace me once more, Hungary!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_06] I have been waiting for you for a thousand years!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Come and once again, when a new day comes at night, come to me!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Come and embrace me once more, Hungary!
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] I have been waiting for you for a thousand years!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Hungary, when I walk on foreign soil, Hungary,
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] the path itself turns toward it, toward it!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] The ancestors with me beg, let me live on in you!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] Just as they live in me, Hungary,
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] may ever greater blessings descend upon me!
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] Hungary, when I walk on foreign soil, Hungary, the path itself turns toward it, toward it!
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] Let the certainty of tomorrow be mine!
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] I only see my own life reflected in me!
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] We are going to the lodging,
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] may ever greater blessings descend upon me!
[SPEAKER_07] [SPEAKER_07] God knows, Hungary!
[UNKNOWN] cucumbers
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN]
[UNKNOWN] HONORABLE MEMBERS OF PARLIAMENT!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you, my dear children, my dear friends, Hungarians at home and abroad!
[UNKNOWN] We warmly welcome you to the free and democratic Hungary!
[SPEAKER_16] Look around at this magnificent square!
[SPEAKER_16] Look into each other's eyes!
[SPEAKER_16] Look along this beautiful city!
[SPEAKER_16] This beautiful country!
[SPEAKER_16] We have not seen so many smiles, so many liberated gazes, and so much hope in Hungary for a long time,
[SPEAKER_16] as we have seen in the past weeks since the April 12th elections!
[SPEAKER_16] Thank you! Thank you! Thank you!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you! Thank you! Thank you!
[SPEAKER_16] Today is not merely the day of the inaugural session of the new parliament.
[SPEAKER_16] Today is the fulfillment of the long, long journey we have taken together in the past years.
[UNKNOWN] The fulfillment of the shared belief that Hungary is indeed capable of rising up again,
[SPEAKER_16] capable of believing in itself once more and capable of being a common homeland for every Hungarian.
[UNKNOWN] Today is not merely the fulfillment of the inaugural session of the new parliament, which we have undertaken together in the past years.
[SPEAKER_16] I would like to go go go go go go
[UNKNOWN] go go
[UNKNOWN] go
[SPEAKER_16]
[SPEAKER_16] go
[UNKNOWN] go
[SPEAKER_16]
[SPEAKER_16] go
[UNKNOWN] go
[SPEAKER_16]
[SPEAKER_16] go
[UNKNOWN] go
[SPEAKER_16] Representatives of the Hungarian people!
[SPEAKER_16] This wonderful day, this story was not written by us, the representatives.
[SPEAKER_16] It was not written in party headquarters, not prepared by background figures, nor by propaganda machines.
[SPEAKER_16] You wrote it through work, love of country, hope, concern, determination, and joy.
[SPEAKER_16] This is now your system change, your homeland, your National Assembly, and we thank you for this!
[SPEAKER_16] You were the ones who set an example to the world, showing that there is no need to be afraid, that one can rise up and set out on a journey.
[SPEAKER_16] You showed the world that even if the galley is above and the water is below, the water is still the master.
[SPEAKER_16] The world learned to say, "The Tisza is overflowing."
[UNKNOWN] The Tisza is overflowing! The Tisza is overflowing! The Tisza is overflowing!
[SPEAKER_16] Today, dear compatriots, today every freedom-loving person in the world would like to be a little Hungarian.
[UNKNOWN] Compatriots, for years they tried to teach us that miracles do not exist.
[SPEAKER_16] They tried to teach us that war is peace, that freedom is servitude, that ignorance is strength,
[SPEAKER_16] that those who think differently are less Hungarian, less valuable, less drunk, less personal.
[UNKNOWN] But did this beautiful country succeed? Did it succeed? No.
[SPEAKER_16] You taught the exact opposite to the country and to the wider world.
[SPEAKER_16] That the most wicked can be defeated by the most ordinary flesh-and-blood people.
[SPEAKER_16] That against the machinery of power, another machinery of power is not needed.
[SPEAKER_16] But rather flesh-and-blood people, who are capable of anything from mailbox to mailbox, house to house, in winter, in frost, in rain, for their country, for their neighbors, for their relatives, for their community.
[SPEAKER_16] There is no greater power than this.
[SPEAKER_16] History will teach in books that light defeats darkness.
[SPEAKER_16] The story, the decency, defeats evil.
[UNKNOWN] Dear friends, you, tens, hundreds of thousands of you, have shown the kinder, more humane face of Hungary.
[SPEAKER_16] This is the Hungary that wants to act.
[SPEAKER_16] This is the Hungary that is cheerful and joyful.
[SPEAKER_16] This is the Hungary that knows no impossibilities.
[SPEAKER_16] Honored fellow citizens!
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] This is your day of celebration.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] We wish to express our gratitude for what we have received from the Hungarian people in the past years, months, and weeks.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] For walking with us on the road.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] For lifting us up when we fell.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] For believing in us even when no one else did.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] For giving this wonderful country the chance to be a happy, free, functioning, and once again humane home.
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] I swear to you, always
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] we will always remember this.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] We will always remember the strength of the freedom-loving, patriotic Hungarian people who brought about change.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Today, we embrace one another, we take each other's hands.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] We thank one another, strangers and familiar faces alike, for being able to stand here in this wonderful country.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] In this wonderful city.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] On this wonderful square.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] In front of the most wonderful building in the world.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] Thank you!
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] My friends!
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] In the past two years
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] I have visited more than 700 settlements in Hungary.
[SPEAKER_16] [SPEAKER_16] I have met countless people.
[SPEAKER_16] I do not have the opportunity to thank each and every one of you individually.
[SPEAKER_16] Therefore, from here, I send my message to everyone who shook my hand, asked me a question, took a photo with me, hugged me, or prayed with me.
[SPEAKER_16] I encourage you, never, never to forget what you have taught me about Hungary.
[SPEAKER_16] In Tarnasadány, Komló, Püspökladány, Ózd, Gyula, and throughout the country.
[SPEAKER_16] What I have received and learned from you, I will carry with me for a lifetime.
[SPEAKER_16] You have not only changed the country, but me as well.
[SPEAKER_16] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_16] I have learned from you that one of the most important tasks in the coming years will be to learn once again to see ourselves as a community.
[SPEAKER_16] Therefore, I ask you to turn to those fellow citizens of ours who are disappointed today, who are afraid, who experience this period as a loss.
[SPEAKER_16] Do not try to defeat them, do not try to humiliate them.
[UNKNOWN] Listen to them, speak with them.
[SPEAKER_16] Tell them,
[SPEAKER_16] that this country is theirs as well, because it belongs to everyone.
[UNKNOWN] That they are also needed, because everyone is needed.
[SPEAKER_16] And that together, together we will rebuild Hungary.
[SPEAKER_16] Because there is no right, no left, only Hungarian.
[SPEAKER_16] And I ask you, I ask you to also turn to those who are in need, who are lonely, who have lost their faith, who feel that no one sees them anymore.
[SPEAKER_16] Because the true strength of a country is not measured by the number of parliamentary mandates the winners hold,
[UNKNOWN] but by how we treat the most vulnerable people.
[SPEAKER_16] And you know this better than anyone.
[UNKNOWN] Many congratulate, but you know them well.
[SPEAKER_16] The real work is just beginning now.
[SPEAKER_16] Now is the time to build communities, to talk, to debate, to help one another.
[SPEAKER_16] And to learn anew, and to show each other that politics can be decent, human, brave, honest, beautiful, and useful.
[UNKNOWN] If it cannot be now, then it cannot be.
[UNKNOWN] But if you are renewed and go home, then politics will be left alone again.
[SPEAKER_16] For without you, we do not want to, and we will not govern.
[SPEAKER_16] Dear fellow citizens, we will represent every Hungarian, but you must do it as well.
[UNKNOWN] I ask you to continue to establish islands, to organize local communities, to get to know each other, to be curious about one another, and to be curious about Hungary.
[SPEAKER_16] We would like to request a medical team for the organizing balloon; people are waving at the Rákóczi statue.
[SPEAKER_16] I ask the organizers to send medical personnel there.
[SPEAKER_16] Be curious about one another, and be curious about Hungary, because this country is full of wonders, full of fantastic people.
[SPEAKER_16] This wonderful country is not the country of hatred, not the country of fear.
[SPEAKER_16] Not the country of hopelessness.
[SPEAKER_16] Hungary is the homeland of talented, free, brave, and decent people.
[UNKNOWN] Hungary is the homeland of talented, free, brave, and decent people.
[SPEAKER_16] Fellow citizens, Hungarians! I would like to ask you to preserve something from this day for everyone.
[SPEAKER_16] Keep this joy, this openness!
[SPEAKER_16] This love!
[SPEAKER_16] Because in the years ahead, Hungary will need this the most.
[SPEAKER_16] Take it with you! Take this day with you as a memory!
[SPEAKER_16] Remember this day for the rest of your lives!
[SPEAKER_16] Remember what Hungary looked like today!
[SPEAKER_16] It may be that one day,
[SPEAKER_16] you will show it to your children, your grandchildren,
[SPEAKER_16] and tell them this was the first day of a free, democratic Hungary in 2026.
[SPEAKER_16] We would like to introduce a little girl who has lost her parents.
[SPEAKER_16] Come up here for a moment!
[SPEAKER_16] Please help her!
[SPEAKER_16] Do you have her?
[SPEAKER_16] There is a little girl here, what is her name?
[SPEAKER_16] There she is, excuse me!
[SPEAKER_16] There, to my left, a lady is raising her hand, there a child has been lost...
[SPEAKER_16] There is a child here, so if anyone is looking for their child, please come over.
[UNKNOWN] So, what I ask of you is to take this day with you as a memory!
[SPEAKER_16] And once again, please allow us to thank you!
[SPEAKER_16] We thank you for your trust, for that completely overwhelming amount of work,
[UNKNOWN] we thank you for the prayers, the kindness, and the encouragement,
[SPEAKER_16] And we thank you for all those many, many kind words and love that we have received.
[SPEAKER_16] And I ask you,
[SPEAKER_16] on behalf of every Hungarian, to celebrate now!
[UNKNOWN] I ask you to embrace one another, to sing, to laugh,
[SPEAKER_16] because a very, very long and often bumpy road has led us here,
[SPEAKER_16] but today we can finally rejoice, and there is something to rejoice about,
[SPEAKER_16] so let us rejoice, and finally let there be dancing!
[SPEAKER_16] Let it be!
[SPEAKER_16] Let me say goodbye,
[UNKNOWN] and I wish everyone here a very good, peaceful, joyful time today,
[SPEAKER_16] and all across the country!
[SPEAKER_16] Thank you for being with us!
[SPEAKER_16] God bless free Hungary!
[SPEAKER_16] God bless every Hungarian at home and all over the world!
[SPEAKER_16] The homeland above all!
[UNKNOWN] Sze cucumbers that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that
[UNKNOWN] To you, how are you! To you, how are you!
[UNKNOWN] Free!
[SPEAKER_06] Csele!
[SPEAKER_06] I will be here!
[SPEAKER_16] Nemetek!
[SPEAKER_16] Csólakos!
[SPEAKER_06] I will be here!
[SPEAKER_06] Zelysz!
[SPEAKER_06] Richter!
[SPEAKER_06] I will be here!
[UNKNOWN] Moldai!
[SPEAKER_06] Barabás!
[SPEAKER_06] I will be here!
[UNKNOWN] Boka!
[UNKNOWN] And who will be here?
[UNKNOWN] The world is big, it lives up to the sky, but there is this earth that trembles in our hands.
[UNKNOWN] Here the leaves fall from the sun, rays fall on you, they draw a path, the planks parade.
[SPEAKER_06] And the space, and the summer, and the pain, that duck, and the wheat, and the house, and the house—where is the boy?
[SPEAKER_16] But at night, like this it's beautiful, we never break apart, come on, tell me, that's what we are!
[UNKNOWN] Hey!
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] Let's stand our ground, if needed, no matter what comes, let the homeland be free.
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] Let's stake our claim here today, so that this one remains, or we die for it one day.
[UNKNOWN] Hey!
[UNKNOWN] [SPEAKER_06] Ho!
[UNKNOWN]
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] If the foot is from Hágyma, and not even a foot, yet they cook here, throw the wheat on it.
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] If the hand is near, my mouth does not drip, we will burn it down, because this is my homeland.
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] This is the yard, this is the village, this is the pain, the pile, this is the harvest, as it grows, this is the stage of glory.
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] Ho!
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] This is the sign, from here onward, we will never run away, come on, tell me, that's what we are, the homeland!
[SPEAKER_06] Hey!
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] Let's stand our ground, if needed, no matter what comes, let the homeland be free.
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] Let's stake our claim here today, so that this one remains, or we die for it one day.
[UNKNOWN] Hey!
[UNKNOWN] [UNKNOWN] cucumbers that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that that
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] Why should we fear, why should we live, if not to be a stronghold?
[SPEAKER_12] Thank you very much to the Csíki Choir, to the Independent Artists,
[SPEAKER_12] as well as to the actors József Funderlik, Zsombor Erzős, Benyámin Dino, László Józan,
[SPEAKER_12] Péter Rajder, Balázs Szántó, András Tóth, and Péter Virág for this unforgettable performance.
[SPEAKER_12] Now, a song is next.
[SPEAKER_04] Attila Szabó's little boy is lost, his mother is waiting for him at the stairs.
[SPEAKER_04] Attila Szabó.
[SPEAKER_12] Before we continue with the next song, an important public announcement.
[SPEAKER_12] The little boy Attila Szabó is looking for his mother, his parents.
[SPEAKER_12] So once again, Attila Szabó is looking for his parents.
[SPEAKER_12] I hope he finds them very soon. Finds them.
[SPEAKER_12] Attila Szabó is looking for his parents.
[SPEAKER_12] Well, Attila is already coming, I hear, he has already been found.
[SPEAKER_12] That is great news.
[SPEAKER_12] Now, after this great alarm, a song follows,
[SPEAKER_12] about which we dreamed as children, and we thought it would be so.
[SPEAKER_12] On stage.
[SPEAKER_12] Ferenc Molnár Karamell.
[SPEAKER_12] Accompanied by piano.
[SPEAKER_12] Kardos Norbert Sándor.
[SPEAKER_09] Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_09] Pride stands before you today.
[SPEAKER_09] Let's have an old song.
[UNKNOWN] This was my very first song, which completely changed my life.
[SPEAKER_09] A life-changing song.
[SPEAKER_09] Receive it with lots of love, and feel free to sing along with me, okay?
[UNKNOWN] Good.
[SPEAKER_06] Good.
[SPEAKER_06]
[UNKNOWN] Good.
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_06]
[SPEAKER_06] Good.
[UNKNOWN] Good.
[SPEAKER_09] Good.
[SPEAKER_09]
[UNKNOWN] Good.
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_09] Good.
[SPEAKER_09] And nothing hurt me.
[SPEAKER_09] There was always some melody in my soul.
[SPEAKER_09] I knew I could say anything in a song.
[SPEAKER_09] And if I wanted to, I could fly away from here.
[SPEAKER_09] This song will carry me, it will take me on its wings.
[UNKNOWN] But why should only I fly, if others can too?
[SPEAKER_09] Why not give wings in song?
[UNKNOWN] This song is flying now, and it might find you.
[SPEAKER_09] This way you could get to know me.
[SPEAKER_09] So that I too can fly with a melody, to what my heart longs for.
[SPEAKER_09] I fly clumsily toward you now, I give you a song.
[SPEAKER_09] And my heart beats in unison with yours.
[UNKNOWN] Me!
[SPEAKER_09] Me!
[SPEAKER_09]
[SPEAKER_09] [UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_09] I will watch everything, but I long more for Balga.
[SPEAKER_09] Even if you were to say that you don't believe in me.
[SPEAKER_09] I will still know what I must do.
[SPEAKER_09] As long as the song sounds in my heart.
[SPEAKER_09] Where shall I soar in thought?
[UNKNOWN] To everyone.
[SPEAKER_09] I always wait until there is enough strength in my heart, I will never give up.
[SPEAKER_09] Don't even ask, I won't do it, I always fight, understand?
[SPEAKER_09] I will fight as long as my heart can bear it, I will not give up, because always...
[UNKNOWN] To everyone.
[SPEAKER_09] Because always...
[SPEAKER_09] Always...
[UNKNOWN] To everyone.
[UNKNOWN] Because always...
[SPEAKER_09] [SPEAKER_09] To fight...
[SPEAKER_09] [SPEAKER_06] One must fight...
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_06] One must fight...
[SPEAKER_09] [SPEAKER_12] Thank you very much!
[UNKNOWN] [SPEAKER_12] Thank you very much!
[SPEAKER_12] [SPEAKER_12] Thank you very much!
[SPEAKER_12]
[UNKNOWN] [SPEAKER_12] Thank you very much!
[SPEAKER_12] He knows best how to express that feeling when we feel the space is truly ours.
[SPEAKER_12] On stage, Gábor Presser and his musical companions.
[SPEAKER_12] And his musical companions.
[SPEAKER_02] Good day to everyone! Good, good, good! Good day!
[SPEAKER_02] When I wrote the following song,
[SPEAKER_02] I would never have thought I would be 51 years old.
[SPEAKER_02] 51 years later, I would be standing here,
[SPEAKER_02] and playing it for those who hadn’t even been born back then.
[SPEAKER_02] This song has survived every kind of system, regime, and power for 51 years,
[UNKNOWN] soft or hard dictatorship,
[SPEAKER_02] and unfortunately, it has survived...
[SPEAKER_02] Because it outlived the band that first played it,
[SPEAKER_02] because it has been 10 years now,
[SPEAKER_02] since the death of Csomló Tomi, there is no LGT anymore.
[SPEAKER_02] And now it will outlive me too, because...
[SPEAKER_02] És most majd túlél engem is, mert...
[SPEAKER_02] Ladies and...
[UNKNOWN] We'll die! We'll die! We'll die!
[SPEAKER_02] What should I do so you can hear me?
[SPEAKER_08] I'll scream like this!
[SPEAKER_02] Can you hear me now?
[UNKNOWN] Now, really?
[UNKNOWN] No?
[UNKNOWN] Hush!
[UNKNOWN] cucumbers
[SPEAKER_02] cucumbers
[UNKNOWN]
[UNKNOWN] cucumbers
[SPEAKER_08] Heyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyyy
[SPEAKER_08] meg túl könnyed kicsat
[UNKNOWN] hogy egy percet nekem az életem
[UNKNOWN] éjj
[SPEAKER_08] te aki nappal dolgodat végzed
[SPEAKER_08] gépet vezeted és hajtod magad
[SPEAKER_08] és embert gyógyítasz gyereket tanítsz
[SPEAKER_08] és este fáradtod várod az álmodat
[SPEAKER_08] te is a gyöngyök percet az életedből
[SPEAKER_08] vágytam el hogy elmondjam
[SPEAKER_08] hogy elénekeljem hogy tudsz hogy élsz
[SPEAKER_08] hogy elnyit nekem hogy neked szól a gitár
[SPEAKER_08] neked zörög a dolg
[SPEAKER_08] neked gyúlnak a fények és a
[SPEAKER_08] neked írom a dal
[SPEAKER_08] neked énekelem
[UNKNOWN] S cucumbers
[SPEAKER_08] S cucumbers
[UNKNOWN] You, who gave life into my hand, so that he would write a song for you, sit down nicely now, place your hand in your lap, and look into my eyes, and listen to me in silence.
[UNKNOWN] I ask for one more minute of your life, I have decided to tell you, to sing it to you, so that you know you live, that you move for me, that the guitar speaks to you, that the matter trembles for you, that the lights glow for you, and I write the song only for you, I sing it only for you.
[SPEAKER_08] I write the song for you.
[UNKNOWN] I sing it for you.
[SPEAKER_06] I write the song for you.
[SPEAKER_06] I sing it for you.
[UNKNOWN]
[UNKNOWN] I sing it for you.
[SPEAKER_06] I sing it for you.
[SPEAKER_06]
[UNKNOWN] I sing it for you.
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_06] [SPEAKER_12] Thank you very much!
[SPEAKER_08] [SPEAKER_12] Thank you very much!
[SPEAKER_03] [SPEAKER_12] Thank you very much!
[SPEAKER_03] not like this. Thank you very much
[SPEAKER_03] to the performers for accepting
[SPEAKER_03] the invitation, and for
[SPEAKER_03] They made this day legendary.
[SPEAKER_03] [SPEAKER_12] Thank you very much!
[UNKNOWN] Now then
[SPEAKER_03] the repeatedly mentioned
[SPEAKER_03] surprise guest, I am sure that
[SPEAKER_03] everyone remembers April
[SPEAKER_03] 12th, right? It's there
[SPEAKER_03] the joy is there, the
[SPEAKER_03] euphoria is there, and the
[SPEAKER_03] dancing, if you remember
[SPEAKER_03] that.
[SPEAKER_03] A song was played,
[UNKNOWN] and
[SPEAKER_03] Zsolt Hegedű, the incoming
[SPEAKER_03] Minister of Health,
[SPEAKER_03] started dancing!
[SPEAKER_03] Zsolt, where are you?
[SPEAKER_03] Zsolt, raise your
[SPEAKER_03] hand, where are you?
[SPEAKER_03] Raise your hand, let them see,
[SPEAKER_03] He is here!
[SPEAKER_03] Come on!
[SPEAKER_03] Let's give him a round of applause!
[SPEAKER_03] We have the best heads in the world
[SPEAKER_03] the best minister for every ministry,
[SPEAKER_03] the best minister for every ministry, we have rock 'n' roll
[SPEAKER_03] stars like we've never had at home before.
[SPEAKER_03] And if we can manage to
[SPEAKER_03] perform the dance movements,
[SPEAKER_03] then I would like
[SPEAKER_03] everyone to
[SPEAKER_03] adopt this attitude in their heads,
[SPEAKER_03] and the surprise guest,
[SPEAKER_03] who came all the way from England
[SPEAKER_03] and watched the whole day in amazement!
[SPEAKER_03] Gentlemen, it is fitting!
[SPEAKER_03] Let the dance begin!
[SPEAKER_03] Helyémes uraim!
[SPEAKER_03] Jelja, legyen tánc!
[UNKNOWN] cucumbers that that that
[UNKNOWN] Ha-ha-ha!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you very much!
[SPEAKER_06] Thank you very much!
[UNKNOWN]
[UNKNOWN] Thank you very much!
[UNKNOWN] Thank you!
[UNKNOWN] There are animals too! There are animals too!
[SPEAKER_06] There are animals too! There are animals too!
[SPEAKER_06]
[SPEAKER_06] There are animals too!
[UNKNOWN] There are animals too!
[UNKNOWN]
[SPEAKER_06] There are animals too!
[SPEAKER_06] 3, 2, 1, 0
[UNKNOWN] Thank you for watching.
[SPEAKER_03] Thank you for watching.
[UNKNOWN]
[UNKNOWN] Thank you for watching.
[UNKNOWN] Subtitles from the Amara.org community
[SPEAKER_11] Subtitles from the Amara.org community